<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Don Henriquez de Castro, or, The conquest of the Indies a Spanish novel / translated out of Spanish by a person of honour.</title>
            <title>Historia tragicomica de Don Henrique de Castro. English</title>
            <author>Loubayssin de Lamarca, Francisco.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12331520</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12331520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59690</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59690)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 208:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Don Henriquez de Castro, or, The conquest of the Indies a Spanish novel / translated out of Spanish by a person of honour.</title>
                  <title>Historia tragicomica de Don Henrique de Castro. English</title>
                  <author>Loubayssin de Lamarca, Francisco.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 167 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.E. for R. Bentley and S. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1686]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Historia tragicomica de Don Henrique de Castro.</note>
                  <note>Written by F. Loubayssin de Lamarca. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Arber's Term cat.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [4]-[11] and 160-167.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:59690:1"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 12. 1685.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>ROGER L'ESTRANGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59690:1"/>
            <p>DON HENRIQUEZ DE CASTRO. OR, THE CONQUEST OF THE INDIES.</p>
            <p>A Spaniſh Novel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Spaniſh, by a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59690:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59690:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THoſe who have ſeen the Life of <hi>Don Henriquez de Caſtro,</hi> in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> will accuſe me, it may be, of not being a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:59690:3"/>Tranſlator. But I hope, I have made the Work Perfecter in the Tranſlation, than it was in the Original: The Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, ends with the Sacrifice of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> and does not tell us what became of the <hi>Hero</hi> of the <hi>Novel.</hi> To end this Adventure agreeab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I make but one Perſon of <hi>Leonora,</hi> and <hi>Julia;</hi> of which the
<pb facs="tcp:59690:3"/>
               <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Author makes two; and I make <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora</hi> come into the Kingdom of <hi>Chili,</hi> which is, in my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, more accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rules; than to break off, as he does, with the Adventure which hapned to her, when ſhe endeavoured to go out of her Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian's Houſe, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Don Henriquez.</hi> I have alſo Retren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="tcp:59690:4"/>all the Wars of <hi>Italy,</hi> which length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned extreamly the Hiſtory of <hi>Don Eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> and had no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. The Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>John Becaio,</hi> which I took out of another <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Book, altho' of a low Stile, may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Reader by their Variety; and I am of Opinion, that the Accident
<pb facs="tcp:59690:4"/>of the Monkey which ſerves to make the Sex of Princeſs <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia</hi> known, will not be Condemned by him. In ſhort, I have forgotten nothing which might render this <hi>Novel</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting; if the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which I have made in it are not agreeable to ſome, there are others who will have more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and will
<pb facs="tcp:59690:5"/>own their Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me, for the Deſign I had to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59690:5"/>
            <head>Some Books printed, and ſold by <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>BEaumont</hi> and <hi>Fletchers</hi> Plays: in all 51. in large Fol.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shakeſpear</hi>'s Plays: in one large Fol. Volume. Containing 43 Plays.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Brownrig</hi>'s Sermons, in Fol.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s Companion to the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Altar:</hi> In Fol.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Aliſtry's</hi> 40 Sermons: In Fol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Towerſon</hi> on the Creed: In Fol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hudebras</hi> Compleat: In 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Preſent State of <hi>England:</hi> In 2 Vol. in Twelves.</item>
               <item>Enter into the Cloſet: in 12.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Evelin's</hi> Calendarium Hortenſ. in 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rules of Civility: in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mauger's</hi> French Grammar: the
<pb facs="tcp:59690:6"/>Twelfth Edition: in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French</hi> Common Prayer: In 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French</hi> Pſalms: in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French</hi> Teſtament and Pſal. in 12.</item>
               <item>Moral Eſſays, in 4 Vol. in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plato</hi>'s Apologie of <hi>Socrates</hi> in 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Natural Hiſt. of the <hi>Paſſions</hi> in 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Idolatry: In 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Hoſt-worſhip: In 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby's</hi> Anſwer to <hi>D. Creſſey</hi> In 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proſpect of Humane Miſery: in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi>'s Vanity of Arts and Sciences: 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bp. <hi>Andrew's</hi> Devotions: In 12.</item>
               <item>—His Manual for the ſick: in 12</item>
               <item>Perſwaſives to the Commun. By the Author of <hi>Enter into thy Cloſet.</hi> in 12.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59690:6"/>
               <head>DON HENRIQUES DE CASTRO, OR THE Conqueſt of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Atlantick</hi> Iſland had remained undiſcovered to all the Nations of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> for many Ages; for <hi>Veſputius Americus,</hi> who diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it, and gave it his Name, did not ſettle there any Collony. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellanus</hi> made a Voyage thither, and ſoon came to the knowledge of the great Riches which might
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59690:7"/>be had from thence; but he could not perſuade any of the Princes, that reigned in his time, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Conqueſt of it. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, being ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more Penetrating, or more Ambitious than his Predeceſſors, hearkened to the Propoſitions that were made to him by <hi>Ferdinando Cortes,</hi> and <hi>Pizarro,</hi> of ſending thither and Army. He furniſhed them with Ships, Forces, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and allowed them to carry the War againſt <hi>Montezuma</hi> into <hi>Mexico,</hi> and againſt <hi>Atabalipa</hi> into <hi>Peru.</hi> They neither of them found much difficulty in ſubjugating thoſe Nations, which had always lived in Softneſs and Voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and which had no knowledge of the Revolutions and Diſturbances practiſed in <hi>Europe.</hi> The ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing effects of the Artillery and Fire-Arms, terrified them in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that they thought it would be to oppoſe the will of Heaven, to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59690:7"/>fight with Men, who had the command of its Thunder-bolts (for ſo they called thoſe terrible En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines which carried Death to them from ſo great a diſtance). The good Fortune of <hi>Pizarro</hi> was, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, not ſo conſtant as that of <hi>Ferdinando Cortes. Don Diego de Almagro,</hi> who had ſhared with him in the Glory of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this happy Climate, could not bring himſelf to ſubmit the Command of the Army to him. They had often ſmall Quarrels, which at laſt broke out into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen War. Each had his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and there were ſeveral Fights between theſe two Chiefs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each, in his turn, was Conquerour and Conquered. This Diviſion was equally fatal to both, and the ill blood which was bred between the two Parties, laſted even after the death of their Generals. <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divia,</hi> whom the Emperour, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, had ſent to ſupply the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59690:8"/>place of <hi>Pizarro,</hi> and to puniſh the Authors of the Revolt, executed the Orders of his Maſter with great ſeverity, ſo that thoſe who had had any hand in the Conſpiracy, hoping for no more favour than thoſe they had already ſeen die by the Hands of the Executioners, went into the Province of <hi>Chilli</hi> for Sanctuary, where <hi>Ruminagui,</hi> Son in-Law to <hi>Atabalipa,</hi> Governed This Prince received the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents with joy, and having had time to examine, near to him, the Arms which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had made uſe of to overcome the King of <hi>Peru,</hi> he found there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Supernatural in them; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he endeavoured to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Indians,</hi> who were of his Party, and to reſcue them from that Fear, which made them take the <hi>Spaniards</hi> for Demi-Gods; he made them underſtand, that ſince all the advantages they had over them, proceeded only from thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59690:8"/>Arms, the uſe whereof they knew not till then, it would not now be difficult for them to drive out theſe Uſurpers, by the means of the Succours which were come to them. <hi>Don Alonſo de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varuvias,</hi> who had put himſelf at the Head of the Rebels, thought it beſt to begin the War with an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie enterpriſe, thereby to raiſe the Courage of the <hi>Indians,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of what <hi>Ruminagui</hi> had endeavoured to inſinuate into them. <hi>Pizarro</hi> had built a Fort in the plain of <hi>Tucapel,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the plain, where he had but a hundred Men in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thinking that number ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in the Submiſſion and Terror wherein all thoſe of the Country were; and as thoſe which he had put in this Poſt, had no opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of exerciſing their Valour, they thought of nothing but of diverting themſelves, and lived in as great a quiet, as if they had been at <hi>Sevill,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59690:9"/>or at <hi>Saragoſe. Don Alonſo</hi> ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in this negligence, and having Marched all Night, came by Day-break before the place; he immediately Stormed it, and having ſcaled it, made himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it before Night. The <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who had the Cruelty, (which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had uſed towards all of their Nation) freſh in their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, would give quarter to none of thoſe they found in the Fort, nor would they pardon the things that were inanimate; for they immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately entirely razed the place, that there might remain no monument to Poſterity, of their having groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the yoak of thoſe Cruel Tyrants. They, after this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, marched fiercely againſt <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divia,</hi> who was the fortifying <hi>Penco,</hi> one of the moſt famous Ports of the Province of <hi>Chilli.</hi> This General, who had notice of their march, might have waited for them in the Town, which was in good
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59690:9"/>Condition enough, to have made a long reſiſtance; or he might have defended the entries of the Lanes, through which they muſt have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily paſt, to come to him; but deſpiſing Enemies, which he had always beaten, he went out to meet them in the plain, thinking aſtoniſh them with his undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but the <hi>Indians,</hi> incouraged by the Remonſtrances of <hi>Rumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui,</hi> and by the taking the Fort of <hi>Tucapel,</hi> far from taking fright, as they had been accuſtomed to do, whenſoever they ſaw the <hi>Spaniards</hi> appear, put themſelves in Battel, under the Command of <hi>Covaruvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> with as great Diſcipline, as if they had been experienced Forces. <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> took the command of the right Wing, leaving that of the left to <hi>Ruminagui. Valdivia,</hi> gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelf by the Diſpoſition of the Army of the Enemies, put himſelf at the Head of the Forces, which were to engage the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59690:10"/>leaving to <hi>Don Henriques de Caſtro,</hi> the Care of attacking the <hi>Indians.</hi> This young <hi>Spaniard</hi> had given ſo many Proofs of his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that <hi>Valdivia,</hi> made no difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of intruſting him with ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a Command, and to prefer him before many old Officers, who bandy'd for it. <hi>Don Henriques</hi> did not belye the good Opinion which his General had conceived of his Valour; he, at the firſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, broke through the beſt Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians of the <hi>Indians,</hi> till he came to that which <hi>Ruminagui</hi> Commanded in perſon; and although this Prince did all that could be expected from a great General, yet he could not hinder his Forces from giving way, and taking flight at the ſight of a Man, who carry'd Death wherever he directed his Steps: <hi>Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> purſued the Run-aways with ſo much heat, that he came with them to the ſame place, where the Fort of <hi>Tucapel</hi> had been, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59690:10"/>the <hi>Indians</hi> had razed the Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. He there made a hault, and drew up his Men again in Battel, for fear leſt the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhould ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and, ſurpriſing him, might take from him a Victory, which he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon himſelf as ſecure of: He left therefore the purſuit of the Run-aways, and returned to the Field of Battel, where he found <hi>Don A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonſo</hi> Conqueror of the left Wing of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, which he had entirely defeated. The two Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals were, notwithſtanding, ſtill engaged in a private Combat, with a Party of Choſen Men, diſputing weakly the Victory with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. <hi>Valdivia</hi> could not take any advantage of the Succors that <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> ſo opportunely brought him, for <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> doubling his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, at the ſight of the new Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which came to attack him, made, by the Death of the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Valdivia,</hi> Victory declare it ſelf on his ſide; thoſe who fought
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59690:11"/>in his Defence, loſt Courage, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him fall, and breaking in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on thoſe which <hi>Don Henriques</hi> led up again to the Fight, drew them along with them, notwithſtanding the Generous endeavour of their Chief, who was at laſt himſelf for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to follow the Multitude. This cruel turn of Fortune, put him into ſo great a Conſternation, that he marched the reſt of the Day, without knowing whither he went; in this Profound Melancholy, he went ſo far from the Field of Battel, that he found himſelf, at the beginning of the Night, at the foot of a high Mountain, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Mirtles</hi> and <hi>Palm-Trees;</hi> this Hill, which ſeemed to bound his Courſe, ſtopped him, and made him, for ſome time, ſuſpend that Grief which poſſeſt all his thoughts; and feeling his Horſe, which had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many Wounds in the fight, fail under him, he lighted, that he might not fall under him. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59690:11"/>Night was ſo dark, that <hi>Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> would eaſily have reſolv'd to ſpend all the Night in this place, leſt he ſhould loſe himſelf, by venturing to climb up the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, if the <hi>Moon,</hi> which roſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at the ſame time, had not by its Light, ſhewn him a Croſs which was ſet up upon the ſide of it; he thought, by this Mark, that it had been inhabited by Chriſtians; ſo he endeavoured to get up, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his wearineſs; when he was come thither, he found no Habitation, but only the entry of a dark Cave, before which this Croſs was erected, he perceived at the end of this Cave a Light, and therefore thought he might there take the reſt which he had need of; he had not advanced ſix ſteps before he diſcovered a terrible Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſeemed to guard this dark Habitation; this furious Beaſt, which was lain down, roſe as ſoon as he ſaw <hi>Don Henriques</hi> appear,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59690:12"/>beating his ſides with his Tail, and beginning to Roar in a moſt hidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner: The <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as brave, as he was, was ſurpriſed at ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for an Accident, and did not know whether he had beſt leave this furious Beaſt in his retreat, or ſecure to himſelf, by his Death, this <hi>Grotto,</hi> which ſeem'd to him, in the deplorable Condition to which he was reduc'd, abſolutely neceſſary for him. But a new Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſoon made this Diſpute with himſelf ceaſe, for he ſaw come from the end of the <hi>Grotto</hi> a young Man, who having made the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on retire, demanded of him, what he lookt for in this ſolitary Place. <hi>Don Henriques</hi> told him, that he had loſt himſelf in the Path of the Mountain, and deſir'd him to give him a retreat for that Night only; he made no difficulty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this new Gueſt into his Subteranean Habitation, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-brought him to the further
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59690:12"/>end of the <hi>Grotto,</hi> did not Charm him leſs by his good Meen, than by the obliging Air with which he receiv'd him. <hi>Don Henriques</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo admir'd the docile Temper of the Lyon, which obeyed all his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as if it had been a little Dog. <hi>Don Henriques</hi> had the leaſure to conſider the Charms of his Land-Lord, by the light of a Stick, of that Aromatick Wood which the <hi>Indians</hi> make uſe of in the dark, inſtead of Candles, and ſeeing him have a delicate Complection, which did not agree with the plainneſs of his Houſe-hold-ſtuff and lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he took him for an Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all the Objects, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to his Eyes, for deluſions, which would vaniſh at the return of the Light. <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> for ſo was this ſolitary Perſon called, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerved the aſtoniſhment of his Gueſt, endeavoured to make it ceaſe with theſe words. <q>I find <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that you are ſurprized to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59690:13"/>ſee this Cave inhabited by a man of my Age; you can hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, in ſo great a Youth, I can abandon all thoſe Pleaſures which others ſeek after with ſo much earneſtneſs. I know very well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that you can hardly imagine, that a Man, who has not yet had the time to ſtudy. Nature, ſhould find out the way to tame the fierceſt of all Beaſts: if I were of the humour to gain praiſes by a Lye, I might tell you, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Father a Philoſopher, who had taken care to cultivate my mind early, and that he having imparted to me much of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he had acquired, I have choſen this ſolitude to be at more leiſure, for the ſtudy of the moſt refined Sciences; but I am ſincere, and I will not ſurprize your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, by a diſguiſe, ſo unworthy of a Man of Honour. I will confeſs to you, that this Cave is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by a reverend old Man, who has entruſted me, during the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59690:13"/>Journey which he is now gone towards the Sea-ſide, with this Houſe-hold-ſtuff which he uſes, and the Lyon, which feeds him with the Prey he catches for him. Was it he, interrupted <hi>Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques,</hi> who tamed this terrible Beaſt? No, replied <hi>Garcia,</hi> it was the work of a Man, who retir'd into this <hi>Grotto,</hi> and who at his death, left it to the Perſon who has allowed me a ſhare in theſe Lodgings, and gave him all his goods, which conſiſted of ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, made of the Bark of Trees, five or ſix Cups of <hi>Coco,</hi> a Covering which he had made of Palm-Tree-leaves, and a Pillow of Bearskin, ſtuft with dried Leaves; he had bred this Lyon from its Youth, and having taught him to bring his Prey to him, he gave him at his death to his ſucceſſour, who has always made uſe of him with the ſame ſucceſs. If you will go to the bottom of this <hi>Grotto</hi> with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59690:14"/>me, you may there Sup upon a remainder of Veniſon which the Lyon has brought, and ſome Dates which I gathered this Morning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Mountain; there is a Fountain, which comes out of this Rock, which will furniſh you with very freſh water to drink, and you may afterwards repoſe your ſelf upon the Bed of Moſs, where I was firſt lain, when you firſt came into the <hi>Grotto.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Don Henriques</hi> very chearfully accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of theſe offers which were made him, and went with him to the bottom of the <hi>Grotto,</hi> and there made with him a ruſtical Meal of the Proviſions which they there found. It being already late, <hi>Don Henriques</hi> had no ſooner Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but he endeavoured to take that reſt, which he had ſo much need of, upon the Bed of Moſs, which was ſo kindly offered to him. In lying down, he let fall a Picture-Box, ſet with Diamonds, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59690:14"/>
                  <hi>Don Garcia</hi> took up, and as he was going to reſtore it to <hi>Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,</hi> it opened, and diſcovered to him a Picture, the Features of which were not unknown to him; after having looked upon it ſome time, he preſented it to him to whom it belonged, ſaying to him, <q>
                     <hi>Pray, Sir, do me the favour, to let me know how this Picture of</hi> Julia <hi>fell into your hands? The Lady, which it repreſents,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>was never called by the Name of</hi> Julia; <hi>ſhe was a</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Lady, and her Name was</hi> Leonora; <hi>I loved her to her Grave, the memory of her being ſtill ſo dear to me, that I cannot think of her without ſhedding of Tears. I have ſeen,</hi> replied <hi>Don Garcia, a Picture, very like this, in the hands of the old Man, who has here choſen the place of his retirement; he keeps it with a great deal of care; it is of a young Woman, of whom he had all the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of a Father; and although he loſt her in</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59690:15"/>he was there a Slave, he is not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to forget her. This being the ſame</hi> Julia, <hi>which I juſt now ſpoke of I have a great Curioſity to hear th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Adventures of</hi> Leonora, <hi>who reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles her ſo perfectly; and I ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> infinitely obliged to you, if after yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have taken ſome repoſe, you will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pleaſed to make me ſome relation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> it. My mind,</hi> replied <hi>Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, is diſturbed with ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent thoughts, that I cannot hope ſleep will have the power, for a great while, to ſhut my Eye-lids; and therefore am very willing, whilſt we are alone, to ſatisfie your Curioſity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not keep you any longer in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Don Henriques</hi> ſeeing <hi>Don Garcia</hi> ſhew, by his ſilence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he was diſpoſed to hear him, began his Hiſtory in theſe terms.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59690:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Hiſtory of</hi> Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, <hi>and</hi> Leonora.</head>
                  <p>MY Name is <hi>Don Henriques de Caſtro,</hi> and I am Son to <hi>Don Lorenzo.</hi> By this account, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> embracing him, I have the Honour to be your Brother, ſince I owe my Birth to this ſame <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> who diſtinguiſht himſelf ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Conqueſt of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru;</hi> I am the only Iſſue of his Marriage with <hi>Hiſmelia,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to King <hi>Montezuma.</hi> I never heard, <hi>replied</hi> Henriques <hi>very coldly,</hi> of this ſecond Marriage. It would have been hard, <hi>replied</hi> Garcia, for you to have heard of this Marriage, ſince it was made in the <hi>Indies,</hi> whilſt you were in <hi>Spain.</hi> I will, if you deſire it, relate to you the Circumſtances of it, when you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59690:16"/>have made an end of your Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Don Garcia <hi>ſaid no more, that he might give his Brother time to purſue his Diſcourſe, which he did after this manner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Since you are Son to <hi>Don Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo,</hi> you are not ignorant that he Married, in the <hi>Moluccas, Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Mendez,</hi> a Kinſwoman of the Vice-Roys; and that having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to return into <hi>Spain,</hi> when <hi>Ferdinando Cortes</hi> had made an end of the Conqueſt of <hi>Mexico,</hi> he ſent her before him to <hi>Sevill,</hi> where ſhe was brought to Bed of me. You know, without doubt alſo, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ingaged, with <hi>Pizarro,</hi> in the Wars of <hi>Peru,</hi> it was impoſſible for him ever to ſee his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try again, and ſo I ſhall only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you with what relates to my ſelf.</p>
                  <p>When I was of an Age fit to bear Arms, I reſolved to go to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> to my Father, but Love ſtayed me for a while in <hi>Spain.</hi> A Kinſman
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59690:16"/>of my Mother, who had long ſerved the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and made ſeveral Voyages to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for the Service of that Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, had a Daughter, who was about ſixteen years old, of an accompliſhed Beauty, as you may gueſs by her Picture. <hi>Don Antonio de Sylva,</hi> for that was the Name of the Father of <hi>Leonora,</hi> who having been a Widdower for a long time, thought it not fit to keep her with him any longer, ſent her to my Mother, whoſe Virtue he was fully ſatisfied of; he writing to her a Letter, wherein he deſired her to take care of the Education of his Daughter, until he returned to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> The Charms of <hi>Leonora,</hi> made me now forget the deſign I had taken to go to the <hi>Indies,</hi> to learn there the Art of War. I was always with her, and I took ſuch pleaſure in her Converſation, that I could not take up a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be from her, although I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59690:17"/>had a violent deſire to gain a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the World. <hi>Leonora</hi> had ſeen ſeveral Courts, and her Mind was far more cultivated, than could have been expected of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Age; her Coverſation ſerved to form mine, and I made uſe of that pretence, to excuſe the ſtay I made at <hi>Sevill,</hi> at a time, when I ought to have been ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſing my Courage, to ſupport the Reputation which my Anceſtors had acquired. <hi>Leonora</hi> was pleaſed to impart to me ſo much of her knowledge, that ſomtimes I was confounded at it; and not having deſerved her Favours, I perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelf, for ſome time, that ſhe did thus only to ſhew her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for the care my Mother took of her. But Love being of a piercing ſight, I ſoon perceiv'd that it was an Impulſe of a more preſſing concern, and that ſhe had not leſs tenderneſs for me, than I had for her. I had a mind to have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59690:17"/>the pleaſure to make her explain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t her ſelf; ſo, one day, finding my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elf alone with her, I ſpoke to her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n theſe Terms: <q>Deareſt Siſter, <hi>(for ſo uſed I to call her,)</hi> will not you find your ſelf too much diſturbed, with the Trouble I give you every day? Will not my Ignorance cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in you a ſcorn of me? And if you continue to inſtruct me with the ſame Goodneſs you have done, how ſhall I ever be able to be grateful enough, for ſo obliging a Care? By making me Reign (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Leonora</hi>) Soveraign in your Heart, it ſeem'd to me, when I firſt ſaw you, that we were born for each other; and I think I reap an advantage for my ſelf, when I inform your Mind of any thing. It has all the Diſpoſitions Nature could give it, of learning every thing neceſſary with eaſe; and it wants only a little Experience, which time will afford. I applaud my ſelf, for your being ſo apt to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59690:18"/>learn by my Inſtructions, and I ſhall be very glad to ſee you one of the beſt bred Men in <hi>Spain,</hi> if you have no deſign to pleaſe any body but my ſelf. You may aſſure your ſelf of that, <hi>I reply'd, taking one of her fair Hands, which I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly kiſſed.</hi> You alone ſhall make all my happineſs, and I will po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh my mind, only to make my ſelf worthy of you.</q> We had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Converſations much like to this, and I thought my ſelf the happieſt of all men. But Fortune was wearied with favouring me. <hi>Leonora</hi> loſt her Father, and altho' ſhe became, by his Death, one of the richeſt Heireſſes in <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhe was extreamly grieved at it. I ſcarce had time to wipe away her Tears, before ſhe was forced to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me the ſame Office; for my Mother ſoon after fell ſick and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Leonora,</hi> who could not decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly live alone with me in the ſame Houſe, went to lodge at the Houſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59690:18"/>of <hi>Don Thomas de Camboya,</hi> who was made her Guardian by her Relations. His Wife was one of thoſe falſe reſerved Women, who being out of a Condition of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her ſelf, would have the young Perſons, who are under Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, renounce all the Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions proper for their Age; and fly the Company of them, as if they were Monſters. Altho' <hi>Leonora</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned this great ſeverity, yet ſhe would not ſee me againſt her Will, leſt ſhe might give her an occaſion of ſuſpecting her behaviour. She felt very ſenſibly the trouble which this ſeparation cauſed in me. But ſince we could not continue our Commerce, unleſs we had a Confident, who might facilitate our Interviews, ſhe endeavoured to know the Character of all thoſe who had acceſs to the Houſe where ſhe was, before ſhe diſcoverd to any one the ſecret of her Heart. She heard that <hi>Don Pedro de Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diel</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59690:19"/>made his addreſſes to <hi>Elvia,</hi> Daughter to her Guardian, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Secret of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and after having done a great many good Offices to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhe confeſſed to him the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe had for me. He offered very civilly to help us to meetings, and he ſeemed ſo zealous for her Intereſts, that ſhe applauded her ſelf with having choſen ſo generous a Confident. But <hi>Don Pedro</hi> was not ſo ſincere as he affected to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, he appli'd himſelf to <hi>Elvia</hi> only out of Policy, he felt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Love for her, and he having only pretended it, to get acceſs to the Houſe of <hi>Don Thomas,</hi> it was to <hi>Leonora,</hi> that his Vows were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, but whether for the Love he had for her, or becauſe ſhe was a very great Fortune, I do not know; he had not Eſtate enough to pretend to her openly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſign'd to make himſelf be beloved by her, before he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59690:19"/>his intention. The Court which he made to <hi>Elvira,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitated to him the means of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Leonora</hi> at all Hours, and he was overjoyed at being able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her ſecrets, that he might in time break the Correſpondence which ſhe had with me. He brought me a Note from <hi>Leonora,</hi> and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take our intereſt ſo much to heart, that I made no difficulty of diſcovering to him my moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts, he came to give me notice when every Body was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired in the Houſe, and we went together into a By-ſtreet, where <hi>Leonora</hi> ſpoke to me through a lower Window, whilſt <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro</hi> diſcourſed with <hi>Elvira.</hi> No bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knew of our Engagements, and <hi>Don Thomas,</hi> who thought of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for <hi>Leonora</hi> according to her Eſtate and Birth, caſt his eyes upon <hi>Don Diego de Avalos,</hi> who made a conſiderable Figure in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> and who had not leſs Wit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59690:20"/>than Courage; he was inform'd of the Love which this Gentleman had for <hi>Leonora,</hi> and there having been ſome propoſition made to him, from him, but before he would give him a poſitive Anſwer, he deſired to know firſt the thoughts of the young Lady, he went therefore to her one morning into her Chamber, and having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled to her the merit of <hi>Don Diego,</hi> he told her of the deſign he had to marry her to him; ſhe would not abſolutely reject the Propoſition, leſt <hi>Don Thomas</hi> ſhould ſuſpect her Heart was ingaged in favour of ſome other, and that cauſing her to be watched, he might diſcover the Commerce that was between us; ſhe only anſwer'd her Guardian, that ſhe was yet too young, to think of engaging her Liberty, and deſired him not to preſs her to reſolve upon any ſettlement. <hi>Don Thomas</hi> who had a great deal of kindneſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59690:20"/>for <hi>Leonora,</hi> would not impoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing upon her which might trouble her, and leaving her at liberty, he let <hi>Don Diego</hi> know he ſhould render himſelf agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Leonora,</hi> and that when he he had obtained her Love, he ſhould always be very ready to approve of the match. <hi>Leonora</hi> charged <hi>Don Pedro</hi> to give me notice that I had a Rival; and as he had a mind to make uſe of this Conjuncture, to take her out of the Hands of <hi>Don Thomas,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to me with ſo much Art, what I had to fear from the weakneſs of <hi>Leonora,</hi> and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of her Guardian, that he made me in a ſhort time the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſeſt man in the World. <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro</hi> the ſame night contrived a meeting for me with <hi>Leonora,</hi> to whom I expreſs'd all my Fears; ſhe did what ſhe could to ſettle my mind, but it was impoſſible; when ſhe indeavoured to aſſure me, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59690:21"/>
                     <hi>Don Thomas</hi> could not force her inclinations, and that though he ſhould have a deſign to do it, ſhe had courage enough to oppoſe his injuſtice, I thought ſhe ſpoke to me, only to deceive me with more eaſe; in ſhort, ſhe could not ſtill my diſquiets, but by promiſing me ſhe would allow me to carry her away from her Guardian's Houſe. I told <hi>Don Pedro</hi> what we reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and he gave me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, it was not beſt for me to appear my ſelf upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and that it would be much eaſier for him than me, to take <hi>Leonora</hi> out of the Houſe of her Guardian, without being miſtruſted, and to conduct her to the place where I ſhould ſtay for her. How could I miſtruſt a Man, who had till then appeard fo faithful and generous? I approved his thoughts, and gave him a Note to <hi>Leonora,</hi> in which I deſired her not to ſail, within two days, to be in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cony
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59690:21"/>which was towards the little Street, where I us'd to diſcourſe with her, that <hi>Don Pedro</hi> would take care to carry thither to her a Ladder of Silk, which ſhe might make uſe of to come down when ſhe ſaw him appear, and that he would conduct her to the place where I was. She ſent me her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> that ſhe would not fail to do every thing punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as I deſired of her in the Note. I agreed with <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> that I would expect her in an open place which vvas neer to the Houſe, and after having conſidered, ſome time, vvhat vve had to do, vve parted to give order, each on his own part, for the Execution of his Deſign.</p>
                  <p>I did not fail coming to the Rendezvous, ſo ſoon as the Clock had ſtricken Tvvelve, I vvaited there for <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> vvith an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream impatience, and hearing no news of this Traytor, I vvas juſt going to ſeek after him, vvhen
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59690:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59690:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59690:23"/>I ſavv by the light of the Moon come tovvards me a Man, vvith his Svvoord dravvn, vvho vvas fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in retreat againſt ſix others, he defended himſelf vvith great Courage, but they preſt him ſo hard, that he vvould have been forced to yield, had I not taken his part. I could not ſuffer ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal a Combat, and having put my ſelf on his ſide vvith tvvo Servants that follovved me, I quickly ſound the Heat of my Enemies cool. One amongſt them, vvho did not care to fight vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out advantage, told me, that I ſhould make my ſelf guilty, by hindring the execution of juſtice, and that he vvhom I had defended, had juſt then aſſaſſinated one of the moſt conſiderable Men in the vvhole Tovvn, and kill'd one of the fineſt Ladies in all <hi>Spain.</hi> But as I knovv People of that ſort never fail to pretend, thoſe vvhich they carry to Priſon are gulity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59690:23"/>of great Crimes, thereby to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them odious, I gave no credit to what this Man told me, nor would not quit the unknown Gentleman's ſide. Thoſe who would have arreſted him, endured no long fight, and having turned their backs, they left him at liberty to ſhew his thankfulneſs to me. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted him at the firſt word, and deſired him to leave me alone, for a reward of all the ſervice I had done him; but yet I could not be rid of him, till I had accepted of a Diamond Ring which he gave me, that he might, as he ſaid, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time know his deliverer. After he had left me, I did not ſtay long in the place where the fray was, the Impatience which I had, to hear ſome news of <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> forced me to ſeek him out, in the little Street where I was uſed to diſcourſe with <hi>Leonora;</hi> but I left, however, one of my Servants there, that he might ingage <hi>Don Pedro</hi> to ſtay for me,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59690:24"/>in caſe he came to look after me; ſcarce had I ſet my foot in this Street, before I heard a confuſed noiſe of people ſpeaking, and ſaw coming towards me a great many Armed Men, who carried Lanthorns with them; I was advanced too far, to retreat without being ſeen, and thoſe Men could take no other way than that by which I came; all that I could do to eſcape from, them, was to go with my Servant who had followed me, into a houſe which was building, and which I was then very near.</p>
                  <p>We had but juſt hidden our ſelves, when I ſaw come by the ſame place, which I juſt then left, a ſecond Company, which joyned with the firſt; I eaſily perceived that it was the Watch, and that the laſt Comers were thoſe who endeavoured to arreſt my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Friend; they ſpoke of this Action to their Companions, ſo ſoon as they were come to them,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59690:24"/>but it was ſo ſoftly, and I was ſo far from them, that I could not hear them very diſtinctly; having a great deſire to know the Names of thoſe which had been kill'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the murther had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted very near the Houſe of <hi>Don Thomas,</hi> I order'd my Servant to go near to them, and to bring me an account of what he hear'd. The Houſe which we were in, was raiſed but to the ground Floor, and the Youth, to go to them, was to go over a very narrow board, the Night being very dark, and the Lanthorns dazling him, he miſſed his footing, and fell into the Foundations; he had in his Pocket a Piſtol ready cockt, which, unfortunately for him, at the ſame time went off, and ſhot him through the Body. I haſtned to his aſſiſtance, but the Watch-men, being drawn thither by the noiſe, were before me, and taking me for the Author of this Murther,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59690:25"/>ſeiz'd me; they would not give me time to defend my ſelf, but hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me away to Priſon, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoever I could ſay in my juſtification.</p>
                  <p>You may eaſily imagin, Brother, what a deſpair I was in when I was arreſted; I ſaw by this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, all the hopes which I had conceived of poſſeſſing a Perſon, who could alone make all the happineſs of my Life, fruſtrated; that which I had heard, made me fear, with a great deal of reaſon, that the Lady whom the unknown Perſon had killed, was my dear <hi>Leonora,</hi> and I had not any long time the Comfort of being able to doubt of it, for the Guards who had taken me Priſoner, told the Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler that I had killed with a Piſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot, which I had aimed at <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> a Woman who was coming down by a Silk Ladder out of a Balcony into the Street, and that <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> indeavouring to revenge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59690:25"/>her Death, had had the ſame Fate. Although I perceived they took me for the Stranger, whom I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued from their hands; yet I could not therein find any thing to make me doubt of my unhappineſs; and I had the more reaſon to be afflicted, becauſe I my ſelf had taken up the Defence of him who had aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Friend and my Miſtreſs. I paſſed the Night in ſo great an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, that I felt no more my Grief, by feeling it too much. The next morning, when I was dreſt, I went down to the Court; I found my ſelf immediately incompaſſed by a great number of Priſoners, who told me, I muſt pay them my welcome; as if it was a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to me, to become a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with them in their Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; I was forced to give them the little Mony I had about me, to deliver my ſelf from their Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; they ſent immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Wine, with which they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59690:26"/>made themſelves ſo Drunk, that ſix of them, who lay in a Garret, let fall their Candle in a Bed, which immediately ſet Fire to the Bed-Mat, and the Rafters of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret being very dry, they flamed out immediately: The Turn-keys, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Round, perceiving the Fire, ran all affrighted, to endeavour to quench it. In this Fright they left open a great Dungeon, where there lay above fifty Priſoners, who having ſeized the Keys, went and opened the Doors of all their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Priſoners, making the word Liberty ſound throughout the whole Priſon; they then broke open the Priſon Gates with ſome great Blocks they found in the Kitchin. I ſuffered my ſelf to be carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the Throng, and I found my ſelf in the Convent of the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliers,</hi> without knowing how I was carried thither; and I being one of the moſt conſiderable of thoſe who had taken Sanctuary
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59690:26"/>there, theſe good Fathers came to Compliment me, and promiſed to let me out, the beginning of the next Night, by a back Door of their Garden, in the Habit of a Monk. I anſwered their Civility as well as the diſturbance my mind was in would allow me; and was Conducted into a Cell, until they brought me what was neceſſary for my Diſguiſe. After I was thus diſguiſed, they led me out of the Convent, with another Priſoner dreſt in the ſame manner, who was to be my Companion; we walked through the Town in this Equipage, without being taken notice of by any Body; and having paſſed the Gate of <hi>Xerez,</hi> we entred the High way which leads to <hi>Cadez,</hi> having followed it ſome time, we left it to get into a Wood, which is about three Leagues from the Town, where we ſtaid in the day time, not daring to Travel but by Night. We ſent, in the mean
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59690:27"/>while, a little Boy, which the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> had given us, to get us ſomething to eat; and we ſate our ſelves down upon the Graſs, in a place where the Trees were thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, that we might have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their ſhade. I began to be in ſo deep a ſtudy, that I did not think of him who was by me; his Mind was more at liberty; and having by chance caſt his Eyes upon the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Ring which I had upon my Finger, knew it to be that which he had given me; and embracing me with a great deal of Affection, <hi>Suffer me</hi> (ſaid he to me) <hi>to ſhew my Gratitude to my Deliverer.</hi> I found by his Diſcourſe and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that it was the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Perſon, whoſe Defence I had ingaged my ſelf in, and that I ſuppoſed to be the Author of the Death of <hi>Don Pedro</hi> and <hi>Leonora;</hi> but the more to clear my Doubt, I deſired him to tell me why the Bayliffs would have arreſted him,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59690:27"/>and he ſatisfied my Curioſity in this manner. <q>
                        <hi>I loved,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>one of the fineſt young Ladies in the Town, her name was</hi> Leonora.</q> At this Name I ſent out a great ſigh, but he took no notice of it, but thus purſued his Diſcourſe, <q>
                        <hi>Her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons approved of my Suit, but her Inclinations were not favourable to me: I had notice given me of the Commerce which ſhe had with a more happy Rival, by a Maid which I had gained, and deſiring to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of it my ſelf, I paſſed ſeveral Nights under her Window, without diſcovering any thing which could ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my Curioſity: But, one Night, ſitting upon a Stone, which lies over againſt the Houſe of</hi> Don Thomas, <hi>I ſaw two Men come near the Balco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which is next to the Chamber of that Fair ungrateful Lady; one of them ſtepping forwards, made a ſign by throwing two little Stones againſt the Window; ſhe immediately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and came down out of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59690:28"/>Balcony by a Silk Ladder to this Man, who had fixt it at bottom with a Stone, that it might be the firmer. I could not any more doubt but that it was to follow the Rival, which was preferred, by her, before me; and being no more Maſter of the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports of my Jealouſie, I thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> nothing but Revenge. I cocked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Piſtol which I had at my Girdle, and fired it upon him, juſt at his Breaſt but he, with his hand, making my Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol mount, it ſhot</hi> Leonora, <hi>who was upon the Ladder; ſhe fell down dead immediately, and her Lover<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who was witneſs of his Misfortune, came upon me like a mad man; he attacked me with ſo little Caution, that he ran himſelf through with my Sword, which I had drawn as ſoon as I ſaw him come towards me. When I was rid of my Enemy, I ran to</hi> Leonora <hi>to give her ſome aſſiſtance, thinking ſhe was only in a Swoon, but I ſoon was convinced, to my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream grief, that her Wound was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59690:28"/>I was not yet come to my ſelf, from the ſurprize which this Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune had cauſed in me, when I found my ſelf attacked by ſeveral Men at the ſame time. What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſoever I had to hate Life, I thought I was bound then to preſerve, to make a voluntary Sacrifice of it to her, of whoſe Death I was the cauſe. In the apprehenſion which I had of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incloſed by my Enemies, I gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a narrow Lane, where I could not be attacked but before; but whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver advantage this Poſt might give me, I ſhould never have been able to reſiſt long mine Enemies, without the aſſiſtance which you ſo opportunely afforded me; and ſince I have been ſo happy, as to find out my Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor by the Ring, which he was pleaſed to accept as a ſmall token of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, he may aſſure himſelf, that I will expoſe for his ſake, upon all occaſions, the life which he has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to me. I did not enjoy long the happineſs which you procured for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59690:29"/>me, for being wounded in many places, I could walk but very ſlowly; and the Watch had time to return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain upon me in greater number: I ſeeing that my reſiſtance would be to no purpoſe, therefore ſuffered my ſelf to be carried to Priſon, without drawing my Sword; you know the reſt, ſince we recovered our Liberty by the ſame way; and I have nothing more to tell you, but that I am call'd</hi> Don Diego d'Avalos, <hi>and that</hi> Don Thomas <hi>had promiſed me to marry this</hi> Leonora <hi>to me, whoſe Life I ſo unfortunately took away.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I was aſſured that <hi>Leonora</hi> was dead, I was pierced with ſo kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Grief, that I could give no more attention to the Relation, with which <hi>Don Diego</hi> went on. I was yet buried in a deep Study, when he left off ſpeaking, and he was forced to pull me by the Arm to bring me out of it; but having my mind filled with Deſpair, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of anſwering his Civility, I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59690:29"/>broke out into theſe Reproaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. <q>
                        <hi>Finiſh, cruel</hi> Don Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, <hi>what you have begun, and take from me a Life, which can now be of no other uſe to me, than to make me the longer endure the Evils which you have cauſed me; you have aſſaſſinated a Miſtreſs which could alone make me happy, when I was juſt going to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs her, and yet far from puniſhing thee, I took thy Defence againſt thoſe who endeavoured to revenge it; nay, I have done more, coming out of the Priſon, where we were ſhut up, I have made thee the Companion of my Fortune, what can you do to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo many Favours? but what would your Gratitude ſignifie to me, ſince you cannot reſtore to me that Treaſure, which your Inhumanity robbed me of?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Diego</hi> was ſo ſurpriſed, with a Diſcourſe which he ſo little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that he was a long time without being able to ſay any thing to me in his juſtification;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59690:30"/>when he was recovered of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, which my Complaints had caſt him into, he threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at my feet, he embraced my knees, which he bedewed with his tears, and ſaid ſo many moving things to me, that what Love ſoever I had for <hi>Leonora,</hi> I could not have had the hard-heartedneſs to have refuſed her to him, if I could have brought her to life again; but that being impoſſible, I contented my ſelf, with ſwearing to him invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Friendſhip, which neither ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence nor time have been ever able to weaken.</p>
                  <p>When the Boy, which was ſent to Town, was returned; we eat the meat which he had brought us, and after having retaken our ordinary Habit, and put our ſwords by our ſides which he had brought us out of the Town, we continued our journey. When we were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> we went to a Houſe of a Friend of my Fathers, where
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59690:30"/>we remained conceal'd, till we had heard the ſucceſs of our Affair. We ſent a skilful Man to <hi>Sevil,</hi> who at his return told us, that they had ſent to Priſon all thoſe who came out of the Sanctuary, and that the Officers of Juſtice endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to take out by force thoſe that remained there, the People roſe up in Arms, and that I was proſecuted upon Contumacy; he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo, that many Witneſſes had ſworn, that I had killed <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> becauſe he had made uſe of my Name to ſteal <hi>Leonora,</hi> and that I could not eſcape being condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death. I ſaw there was no more ſafety to be expected for me in <hi>Spain,</hi> and therefore took up a reſolution of going up to my Father into <hi>Peru,</hi> where I knew he was returned, ſince <hi>Valdivia</hi> had taken upon him the Command of the Forces there. <hi>Don Diego</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my deſign, deſired me to allow him to accompany me in this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59690:31"/>that he might have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſhewing his acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the ſervice I had done him; we heard that <hi>Valdivia</hi> had demanded ſuccours from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, and that there were in the Port five or ſix great Men of War, waiting for a Wind to fail for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru;</hi> we were not willing to let ſo fair an opportunity ſlip, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deſired <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> (in whoſe Houſe we were lodged) to aſſiſt us in our paſſage, he related our adventure to a Captain, who was his intimate Friend, and deſired him to receive us on board. It was not hard to perſwade him to it; this Officer, knowing the great Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration they all had for my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Indies,</hi> thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much honoured with our have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen his Ship ſooner than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers. We ſet fail from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> fifteen days after our arrival; the beginning of our Voyage was pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty proſperous, but in the Latitude
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59690:31"/>of the Iſland of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> we met with a furious Tempeſt, which laſted for two Days, and two Nights. When the ſtorm was cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, we continued our Voyage to <hi>Penco</hi> without any other ill accident happening to us. <hi>Valdivia</hi> came thither ſome days before us, with a deſign to fortifie it; we did not find there my Father, who remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Province of <hi>Quito</hi> with one half of the Army, but were notwithſtanding very well recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> for his ſake, he treated me with ſo much reſpect, when he knew of what I was capable, that he gave me the Command of the left Wing of his Army in the laſt Battel where he loſt his life, and to <hi>Don Diego</hi> that of all the Horſe, for my ſake, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he knew neither of us had ſerved in any Army before. I know not what is become of this generous Friend, but if he be dead, as there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s great Probability he is, I ought
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59690:32"/>very much to regret his Life, ſince he twice ſaved mine in this Battel; he there gave ſo many Proofs of his Conduct and Valour, that he was to be found every where, where there was need of him to defend a weak Poſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Henriques</hi> related after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to his Brother the ſucceſs of this Battel, and how following ſome Runaways, he came to the foot of the Mountain on which they were, and that having loſt his Horſe, he ſought for a Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary in this Grotto, which the Croſs erected before it, made him find.</p>
                  <p>When he had done ſpeaking, being late, he bad <hi>Don Garcia</hi> good Night, and lying down upon the Bed of Moſs where he ſate, fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep; the toyl of the Night before had ſo tired him, that neither the break of day, nor the ſinging of Birds interrupted his ſleep; he had in all likelyhood awaked very late,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59690:32"/>had he not heard ſome great cries, which ſeemed to come from a place not far diſtant from the entry of the Grotto; when he had wholly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed the Vapours of Sleep, he hearkned with more attention, and thought he heard the Voice of <hi>Don Garcia;</hi> he looked about him, and not finding him there, he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not but that his dear Brother had need of his help. He was ſtirred up to do him Service by a ſecret impulſe, the cauſe of which he was ignorant of, and which act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſtrongly in him than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Relation, he took his Sword and went out of the Grotto, he had not gone twenty paces, before he found <hi>Don Garcia</hi> wreſtling weakly with an Ape of a prodige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bigneſs; this Beaſt had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thrown him down, and altho' he held him very ſtraitly imbraced, he did him no other hurt, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuning him with his Careſſes. <hi>Don Henriques</hi> was amazed to ſee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59690:33"/>that the Ape had more diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and knew better the Sex of <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> than he; and if he had not apprehended that this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical adventure might have fatal Conſequences for the ſuppoſed Gentleman, he would have taken pleaſure in diverting himſelf with it, and in making Reflexions upon the advantage which Beaſts have over Men, in the knowledge of things which are proper for them; but the violent Condition, in which he ſaw the feigned <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> would not allow him to go on with thoſe thoughts. He had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready his Sword drawn in his Hand, and ran to the aſſiſtance of this fair diſguiſed Perſon, with all the eagerneſs of a Lover poſſeſt by a ſtrong Paſſion; but the Lion did not give him leiſure to execute his Deſign; he was coming back from his Chace, and having ſeen the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that the Ape uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> whom he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59690:33"/>upon as his Maſter, he ran to his aſſiſtance; his Enemy, vvho look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him as the King of Beaſts, and who found himſelf too weak to diſpute the Victory with him, endeavoured, but in vain, to ſave his Life by flight; the Lyon had ſoon catched the poor Ape, and torn him in pieces, in ſight of the Perſon whom he had affronted. This odd accident ſuſpended, for ſome few moments, the Grief, with which theſe two Perſons were affected, and furniſhed <hi>Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> ſubject enough to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant upon, concerning the perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he had found <hi>Don Garcia</hi> in, he had a mind to perſecute him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what he knew of his Sex; but <hi>Don Garcia</hi> took upon him his ſerious Air, and upheld, with a great deal of boldneſs, what he had firſt pretended; ſo that <hi>Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> did not know what to believe. This fair Counterfeit was greatly concerned to confirm <hi>Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59690:34"/>in his Error; for ſhe thought ſhe could not, with Decency, live alone with a Man of the Age of <hi>Don Henriques,</hi> if he were truly informed of her Sex, and ſhe could not go from the place where ſhe was, without ſuffering many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies. For this reaſon ſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected great ſincerity, the better to deceive <hi>Don Henriques,</hi> and told him, that ſhe could not make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter return to the Confidence he had repoſed in her, than by relating to him, in her turn, the Adventures which had brought her to this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable ſolitary place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Henriques,</hi> who hoped by the means of the Relation ſhe was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make, to clear his Doubts, preſt her to afford him this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; they ſate down under ſome Palm-Trees which were near the Mouth of the Grotto, and <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> after having ſtudied ſome ſhort time, began his Diſcourſe in this manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59690:34"/>
                  <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Don Garcia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SInce you never heard, dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of the Marriage of <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> with the Daughter of <hi>Montezuma,</hi> I ought, before I give you an account of what relates to my ſelf, to inform you what has hapned to him ſince his coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Indies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You know that he having ſet Sail, with <hi>Ferdinando Cortez,</hi> for <hi>Mexico,</hi> a ſtorm ſeparated the Ship, aboard of which he was, from the reſt of the Fleet, and that he was forced to put in at the <hi>Molucca's</hi> to refit; it was whilſt he remained in theſe Iſlands, that he fell in love with your Mother, whom he Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, to have the Protection of the Vice-Roy, whoſe Kinſwoman ſhe was: ſhe was with Child ſoon after
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59690:35"/>her Marriage, and <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> ſent her into <hi>Spain,</hi> whither he hoped, in a ſhort time to come to her, but his unhappy Fate ſtayed him in the <hi>Indies,</hi> where he gloriouſly loſt his Life, as you told me laſt night. <hi>Ferdinando Cortez,</hi> with whom he wentto joyn, ſo ſoon as he was fit to ſet Sail again, having obſerved in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſions, that he was undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt the greateſt dangers, and that he always acted with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great deal of Conduct and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, made him General of his Army: He found no reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent his having givenhim this em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; and he owed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Mexico</hi> to his manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Cortez,</hi> who had not Forces enough, to undertake the Siege of the Capital of that Kingdom, made uſe of <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> to treat with <hi>Montezuma,</hi> and with his <hi>Caſſicoes,</hi> who are the great Men of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, indeavouring to perſuade them what a great advantage they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59690:35"/>would have from an Alliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Nations, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of Merchandiſes brought from <hi>Europe,</hi> with theirs; and the knowledge of the Arts and Trades which are uſed in <hi>Europe.</hi> This Prince had heard ſo much of my Fathers Vertue, and ſincerity, and he ſpeaking to him with ſo much eloquence; my Father obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him what he deſired, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the endeavours that had been uſed to terrifie <hi>Montezuma</hi> by Propheſies, by which it was foretold, that the Monarchy of <hi>Mexico</hi> was to be deſtroyed by a People who were to come from the other end of the World; the King went out to meet <hi>Cortez,</hi> and made him to be carried in a Golden Chair, followed by all his <hi>Caſſicks,</hi> with a moſt magnificent Equipage.</p>
                  <p>He conducted this Illuſtrious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral into his Palace, with the ſound of many Inſtruments of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, after the manner of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59690:36"/>and lodged him there, in a moſt ſumptuous Appartment. But <hi>Montezuma</hi> was ill rewarded for the kind reception he gave to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tez;</hi> for whil'ſt he was a-ſleep in his Chamber, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> General came into it, under pretence of diſcourſing with him, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome important buſineſs, and being followed by ſome Officers, who were entruſted with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſeized not only upon his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but upon all the Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The People provoked by ſo black a treachery, took Arms, and beſieged <hi>Cortez</hi> in the Royal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and they had certainly put all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to the Sword, who were not in a condition to reſiſt ſo great a Multitude, if my Father had not appeaſed the Kings juſt reſentment, and prevailed with him to appear in the Balcony, and command the <hi>Mutineers</hi> to lay down their Arms. <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> did yet more, he treated with <hi>Cortez</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59690:36"/>for <hi>Montezuma</hi>'s ranſom, who promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give him a Pike of Gold in ſquare. This Prince performed on his part, all that he was enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to. But <hi>Cortez,</hi> far from ſetting him at Liberty, as he had promiſed, cauſed him to be ſtrangled with a cruelty beyond example, uſing all his Children with the ſame inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, excepting <hi>Iſmelia</hi> whoſe beauty had charmed this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Tyrant. This Treaſon would have been the deſtruction of all the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> if my Father had not endeavoured to excuſe it to the Princeſs, and perſwaded her that the refuſal which <hi>Montezuma</hi> had made to his General, of accepting of him for his Son in-Law, had forced him to this Violence; he repreſented to <hi>Iſmelia,</hi> that <hi>Cortez</hi> would have been more moderate, if he had been leſs in Love, and that it would be more advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for her to ſit with him upon the Throne of her Fathers, than
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59690:37"/>to undertake to revenge the death of <hi>Montezuma</hi> upon a man that would be ſupported by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Monarch in the World. <hi>Iſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> yielding to his reaſons, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the People, and turned Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; but <hi>Cortez,</hi> who was more Politique than Amorous, would not have his ſafety depend meerly upon the humour of a Woman, fortifyed himſelf in the Palace, and ſent for Ships and Artillery, to keep the <hi>Mexicans</hi> in awe; when he ſaw his Power ſetled, he uſed <hi>Iſmelia</hi> without any reſpect, and looked upon her then but as his Slave. <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> who thought his Honour engaged to ſupport the intereſt of a Princeſs, who had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered her ſelf to be guided by his Counſels, ſpoke of it with ſo much heat, to his General, that he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcovered himſelf her Lover; Jealouſie joined it ſelf to the uſual ſeverity of <hi>Cortez,</hi> who thought himſelf obliged at the ſame time,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59690:37"/>to puniſh <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> for the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which he had ſpoken, and the Charms of the Princeſs, which had been able for ſome time to ſlacken his Courage; but he would not put them to death, he contented himſelf with expoſing them upon the Sea in a <hi>Canoo,</hi> without Oars or Sails, and Proviſion which could laſt them but a few days; theſe two unfortunate Perſons, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been fifteen days a Play-game to the Wind and the Waves, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting nothing but Death, either by a wrack or hunger, when they perceived a far off ſome Ships, they made a ſign to them, with a piece of white Linnen. <hi>Pizarro,</hi> who commanded this Fleet, ſent out his long Boat to take them in; after he came to know the name of my Father, and that of the Princeſs, and the adventure which had reduced them to ſo ſad a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, he condemned the cruelty of <hi>Cortez,</hi> and offered them his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59690:38"/>Protection; he aſſured <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> that it ſhould not be his fault, if his courage was not rewarded; and to give him ſome proofs of this, he deſired him to accept of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Vice-Admiral of his Fleet, which was then newly Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant; he afterwards addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Princeſs, to whom he ſaid he took great part in her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and proteſted to her, that he ſhould always preſerve that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for her, which was due to her Merit and Birth; after <hi>Don Lorenzo</hi> had been received into this new Employment with a diſcharge of all the Cannon, and with the general applauſe of the Fleet, they ſteer'd their Courſe for <hi>Panama,</hi> where <hi>Pizarro</hi> found <hi>Don Diego d'Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magro,</hi> who had been his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. The diſcovery which he had made of <hi>Peru,</hi> this ambitious man, who was in hopes to have an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual power with <hi>Pizarro,</hi> as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward due to his ſervices, could
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59690:38"/>not endure to ſee himſelf fallen from this hope, without ſhewing ſome concern at it, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that he had conſidered only his own intereſt. <hi>Don Loren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo</hi> indeavoured to reconcile them, and by his skill effected it, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with <hi>Pizarro</hi> to give <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro</hi> the command of a Squadron, and was willing himſelf to ſerve under him, the two Generals lived in very good correſpondence during the reſt of the Voyage. And after the Army landed, <hi>Don Diego</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to guard the Ships, whilſt <hi>Pizarro</hi> marched forward into the Countrey; all the Towns which were in his paſſage opened their Gates to him, and he marched directly to <hi>Cuſco</hi> the Capital City of the Kingdom. <hi>Attabalippa,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had notice of his ſucceſs, came againſt him with a great Army, but it was to his ſhame, for he was beaten and taken Priſoner, this Prince promiſed <hi>Pizarro</hi> 200 thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59690:39"/>Marks of Gold for his Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; but whilſt he ſought after pretenſions, to defer the Execution of this Treaty, he hired men to aſſaſſinate <hi>Pizarro:</hi> The <hi>General</hi> would not be his own avenger for this attempt, but left the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to the Council of War, who having heard thoſe that <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabalippa</hi> would have employed in this Action, and finding the Plot ſufficiently proved, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this unhappy Prince to have his Head cut off; which Sentence was executed upon him, at the Head of the Army, which was drawn up in battel to be preſent at it. The news of the death of <hi>Attabalippa</hi> being carried to <hi>Cuſco,</hi> its Inhabitants ſent Deputies to <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarro,</hi> to offer him the Keys of their City, and he ſome few days after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made his entry into it with great Magnificence. <hi>Iſmelia</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Army, being reſolved not to leave <hi>Don Lorenzo;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59690:39"/>come to <hi>Cuſco,</hi> received there the News of the death of <hi>Tereſamendez</hi> your Mother; after time had quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the grief, which the loſs of ſo dear a Perſon had cauſed in him, he thought he could not repair it better than by marrying <hi>Iſmelia,</hi> vvith vvhoſe vertue he had been charmed. This Princeſs lookt upon this marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age as a conſiderable advantage in the change of her Fortune; and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, vvhich had prepoſſeſſed her Heart in favour of <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> made her find ſome ſatisfaction in being able to make a firm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction betvveen their Fates; their Wedding vvas celebrated vvith all the Pomp vvhich the diſorders of War would allovv. A few days after, my Father was forced to leave his new Wife, to go to fight againſt <hi>Rominagui,</hi> Son-in-Law to the deceaſed King, who had gathered together an Army in the Province of <hi>Quitto,</hi> whilſt <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarro</hi> was making an end of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59690:40"/>that of <hi>Cuſco.</hi> Fortune was favourable to both; for <hi>Rominagui,</hi> who was overcome in two Battels, was forced to abandon the Province of <hi>Quitto,</hi> and to retire into that of <hi>Chilli:</hi> My Father would not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him thither, but returned to <hi>Pizarro,</hi> who had ordered him to join with him: This General having had notice, that <hi>Almagro,</hi> being Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Reputation he had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had Landed the Forces which remained in the Ships, and having ſeized upon the <hi>Maritime</hi> Towns, he endeavoured to make himſelf Soveraign of all the Country on the Sea ſide. <hi>Pizarro</hi> marched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with his Army, and ſo intimidated the Mutineers by his diligence, that they ſeiſed upon the Perſon of <hi>Almagro,</hi> and delivered him into his hands, who proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him at a Council of War, which having Condemn'd him, Sentence was executed upon this great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who would have gained a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59690:40"/>great deal of Honour, if he had had leſs Ambition. After his Death every thing remained quiet, and <hi>Pizarro,</hi> who was now joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by my Father's Forces, went to attack <hi>Rominagui</hi> in the Province of <hi>Chilli,</hi> where, in his march, he took in the Town of <hi>Los Royes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Almagro</hi> left a Natural Son, who had ſerved in the Army in conſiderable Employments; this Man, who was bold and underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, reſolving to revenge the Death of his Father, entered, one morning, the Caſtle of the Town of <hi>Los Royes,</hi> where the General was Lodged, and being followed by a company of reſolute Men, who were engaged in the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, by the hopes of a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he ſtabb'd the General in his Bed, and cut to pieces all thoſe who indeavoured to oppoſe his paſſage. The ſucceſs of this Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe having raiſed the Courage of the Friends of Almagro, they took
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59690:41"/>up Arms, and being drawn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an open place, which is in the middle of the City, they made choice of his Son for General of the Army. <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> who thought he had great reaſon to fear the Fury of the Mutineers, by reaſon of the Friendſhip which <hi>Pizarro</hi> had had for him, went ſecretly to <hi>Cuſco,</hi> to take my Mother, whom he found delivered of me, and he carried her with great diligence to the Sea ſide, where he went on board his Ship, before the news of the Death of <hi>Pizarro</hi> had been publiſhed in the Fleet, and retired with her to the <hi>Molucca</hi> Iſlands, where he hoped to be in ſafety, by the Intereſt he had with the Relations of your Mother. He reſolved to ſtay there until he knew the Emperours thoughts, concerning this action of young <hi>Almagro,</hi> and he lived there ten years in great Tranquility. I was about fourteen years old, when <hi>Charles</hi> V. ſent <hi>Valdivia</hi> to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59690:41"/>
                     <hi>Pizarro,</hi> who ſent Orders to my Father, to take upon him again his former Command, which he might exerciſe without any fear of the Mutineers, he having made an Example of their Chief. <hi>Don Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo,</hi> having received this advice, departed, in order to his return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Province of <hi>Chilli,</hi> where this new General then was, and I ſtayed with my Mother, who died four years after the departure of <hi>Don Lorenzo.</hi> When I found my ſelf ſtrong enough to bear Arms, I went on Shipboard to find my Father at <hi>Penco,</hi> of which <hi>Valdivia</hi> had given the Government to him. I had a Siſter younger than my ſelf by ſome years, who was ſo like me, that we were often taken the one for the other, if we were not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by our Habits; and ſhe choſe rather to follow me, than to remain in a ſtrange Countrey alone.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59690:42"/>
                  <p>Our Voyage was happy but the firſt day, for the next day the Wind changed, and there aroſe ſo violent a ſtorm, that we thought every moment we ſhould periſh. My Siſter, who had never before ſeen the inconſtancy of this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, repented more than once of her having undertaken this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; but I did what I could to comfort her, tho' I my ſelf was not wholly void of Fear. Fortune vvhich had a mind to give us ſome reſpite, to make us aftervvards more ſenſibly feel her blows, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Winds, and made the Sea as Calm, as vvhen vve came on board. Scarce had vve eſcaped this danger, before vve found our ſelves expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to another, vvhich vvas much greater; vve diſcovered vvithin Cannon ſhot ſix great <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War, vvhich vve could not ſee before, by reaſon of the agitation of the Waves; we were too near to avoid fighting, and too weak to reſiſt them.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:59690:42"/>
                  <p>We having then Peace with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> we thought they would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us to follow our Courſe, but they coming on board our Ship, under pretence of ſearching for Counterband Goods, made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of it, and made all in the Ship go down into the Hold, but my Siſter and my ſelf, who were carried on board the <hi>Admiral;</hi> we were preſented to <hi>Winch,</hi> who Commanded this Fleet, and we were received by him, with greater Civility, than we could expect from a Man, who paſſed for the moſt terrible Privateer that ſailed upon the Seas. He made excuſes for the ſeverity which was uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe of our Ship, which he pretended were taken in a Fault; altho' I eaſily perceived that this was but a Pretence, to Confiſcate the Merchandiſe we had on board; yet I durſt not but agree with him, in what he ſaid, leſt he ſhould uſe us with more ſeverity. He order'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59690:43"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:59690:43"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59690:44"/>two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captains, which ſerved in his Fleet, to take care of us; and I ſhould have wonder'd what made him treat us with ſo much difference from the reſt, had I not obſerved that he looked upon my Siſter with very paſſionate Eyes.</p>
                  <p>When we were retired into the Cabbin which was allotted for us, a Servant, which was appointed to attend us, came to us, and told us in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> (thinking he was not underſtood by the two Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers who followed us) that he had been ſome time in <hi>England,</hi> and that underſtanding that Language, he ſtayed with <hi>Winch,</hi> after we left him, to learn his thoughts; he added alſo, that he had heard him ſay, That he valued more the Prize he had now taken, than all that he had got ſince he had paſſed the Line, becauſe of a young Lady he had ſent for on board, and which he intended to make his Miſtreſs.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:59690:44"/>
                  <p>After this Youth had ended his Diſcourſe, <hi>Alvarez</hi> and <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> (for ſo the two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Officers were called,) aſſured us, that we needed not be in fear for the Honour of my Siſter, and that they would both dye, together with all their Friends, rather than ſuffer any Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to be uſed towards us. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varez,</hi> to diſperſe our fears with the more eaſe, ſpoke to us thus, <q>
                        <hi>We were, my Brother and I, both born in</hi> Cordua; <hi>we had an Eſtate near to the Town, where one of our Neighbours had a mind to Hunt, and we endeavour'd to hinder him from it, upon which, coming to blows, he was killed in the Fray: We remained ſome time concealed in</hi> Cordua, <hi>in the Houſe of a Friend; but having heard we were Condemned to Death for Contumacy, and our Eſtate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated, we fled into</hi> England, <hi>where we came to be acquainted with</hi> Winch. <hi>It was at the time when he ſet out on his Voyage; and he offering
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59690:45"/>to each of us the Command of a Ship, we were very glad to embrace this offer, when we durſt not return into our own Country; and we ought to think our ſelves extreamly happy, that it gives us an opportunity of doing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Perſons, who are able eaſily to obtain our Pardons from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</hi>
                     </q> After we had returned their Civility, and that we had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured them, that we would uſe all the Intereſt of <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle them again in their Eſtates. We asked their advice, how we ſhould behave our ſelves. After having argued a long time, we concluded that I ſhould change Cloaths with my Siſter, that ſhe might not be expoſed to the violences of the Privateer, and it was not hard to deceive him by our reſemblance. This Caution was not without need, for <hi>Winch,</hi> who was not a Man that uſed to make Love in form, endeavoured to take a freedom with me, which a Perſon of my
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59690:45"/>Birth could not look upon, but as a ſenſible Affront. I upheld the rights of the Sex, of which I had taken the habit, with as much firmneſs as was neceſſary to repreſs his Inſolence. I ſpoke to him thus, with a great deal of reſolution. <q>
                        <hi>Sir, your preſent extravagant acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons anſwer ill the promiſes you made to us, the firſt time we had the honour to ſee you; you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we were taken Priſoners againſt the Law of Arms; and you are not ignorant that</hi> Don Lorenzo, <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, has intereſt enough with the Emperour, to obtain, by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, from the King of</hi> England, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for any Affront which I may receive on board of you. If theſe conſiderations will not make you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have your ſelf otherwiſe towards me, you may be ſatisfied, I deſpiſe Life ſo much, that I will at any time ſacrifice it for the preſervation of my Honour.</hi>
                     </q> Theſe words, ſpoken with an Air, which made him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59690:46"/>the effects would ſoon follow the threats, allay'd the tranſports of his Paſſion; he made the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his Paſſion his excuſe, and told me, gentile enough for a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that ſuch an extraordinary Beauty as mine, did not leave Reaſon free long, and that I ought to accuſe nothing but the force of my Charms, for the Crime which he had now committed. <hi>Winch</hi> would not continue his Diſcourſe any longer the firſt time, for fear of importuning me; he only charged <hi>Velaſquez</hi> to talk to me of his Paſſion, to inform me of his Riches, and to ſpeak to me of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, if an Amorous Concern ſhould alarm my Virtue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Velaſquez</hi> gave me a faithful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Converſation; and we agreed that it was neceſſary to gain time, ſince my Siſter could not do any thing for <hi>Winch.</hi> For <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> having changed the Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being very zealous in his,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59690:46"/>we thought he would never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to have my Siſter married to a Man, who would ingage her in a contrary Opinion. This was the reaſon why we thought there was no other courſe to be taken, than to amuſe <hi>Winch,</hi> until we had Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſome place or other, leſt he ſhould have uſed force. But it was impoſſible for me to effect my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; for the tender things which I ſaid to him, did not content him, his Paſſion required other Favours, which the Body was to have a greater ſhare in than the Mind; and he at laſt was ſo forward, that one day, being provoked by my reſiſtance, he ſpoke to me in theſe terms. <q>
                        <hi>I have hitherto been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not to make uſe of the Right, which War has given me, over your Perſon. I have given you time to diſpoſe your ſelf, to allow me out of Gratitude, what my Love deſerves; and I thought to have ſilenced your Vertue, by offering you to poſſeſs you in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59690:47"/>a lawful way, but ſince you oppoſe my deſires, by an unjuſt reſiſtance, I ſhall be obliged to force from you a Treaſure, which you would not afford me with your conſent.</hi>
                     </q> I endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to find out terms which might allay his tranſports, that I might have time to conſult with my two Protectors what courſe to take. <q>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> replyed I, <hi>I have uſed all my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make my Heart ſenſible of your Paſſion, but you know that</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Ladies live in ſo great a retirement, that the name of Love alone, is capable of affrighting them; you have nothing to combate, but a remainder of a dying Virtue, and I will let you know by</hi> Velaſquez <hi>the meaſures which are to be taken to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So ſoon as <hi>Winch</hi> was gone out of my Chamber, I ſent for the two <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to whom I related our Converſation. We were all of Opinion that it was abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to deſtroy <hi>Winch,</hi> if I had
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59690:47"/>a mind to preſerve the Honour of my Siſter; and after having conſider'd of the means to do it, we reſolved that <hi>Velaſquez</hi> ſhould tell him, my Siſter was incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make him happy, but that ſhe could not effect it in the Ship, without expoſing her ſelf to the ſcorn of the whole Fleet; and that pretending ſhe was willing to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his deſires, he ſhould perſuade him to come near to the Coaſt, which was the ſame where we now are, and to go into his Long-Boat with ſuch Perſons as he could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt with this ſecret, and walk under the Trees, which are at the foot of this Rock, where ſhe might have no Witneſs of her frailty. There being a great likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that <hi>Winch</hi> would ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be taken in this Trap, we thought it fit to have the Supper carried on ſhore, with the beſt Wine which was in the Fleet, and to mix ſome Drugs, which might
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59690:48"/>doze him, in the Wine which <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſquez</hi> ſhould fill for him, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſleep he might be the more expos'd to our Revenge: We thought that after that we might be ſtrong enough to rid our ſelves of the Servants he ſhould bring with him, if they ſhould venture to obſtruct our Deſign. <hi>Alvarez,</hi> on his part, promiſed to engage in our Quarrel, the Lieutenant of the Ship which <hi>Velaſquez</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and <hi>Ablington,</hi> Lieutenant to the Admiral, who had a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate pique to <hi>Winch,</hi> and to make them attack the other three Ships, ſo ſoon as we ſhould give them a ſignal that our undertaking had ſucceeded. After having thus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our meaſures in what we were to do, as well at Land as at Sea, we parted, each to uſe his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, for the promoting of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Deſign. <hi>Velaſquez</hi> was able ſo fully to perſuade <hi>Winch</hi> of the change of my Siſter, that this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59690:48"/>expected night with impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which he hoped would make him happy. So ſoon as the Sun was ſet, he made me paſs in his Long-Boat, into which he ſuffered none to come, but <hi>Velaſquez</hi> with two of his Servants, and a like number he took of his own, which he choſe for their Fidelity. He commanded the Rowers to make to ſhore with all the diligence poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo ſoon as we were Landed he gave me his hand, and led me under the <hi>Banian</hi> Trees, which gave a very agreeable ſhade; there we ſate down, and after having ſpread a Napkin upon the Graſs, they brought us the Proviſions which were for our Supper. <hi>Velaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> took charge of the Bottles, that he might prepare the Wine whereof he intended to make <hi>Winch</hi> drink, but having in vain looked for the Drug which he had a mind to mix with it, he found he had forgotten it in his Ship: But however being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59690:49"/>in a Condition to do that by Force which he had deſign'd to do by Cunning, he aroſe from his ſeat, and pretending to go to reach a Cup, he drew out his Hanger, and ſtruck <hi>VVinch</hi> ſo great a Blow, that he ſevered his Head from his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; he went afterwards and run one of the Privateers Servants through, who was bringing ſome Sweet-meats, which were forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Ship, before he knew of his Maſters Death; he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained fell upon his Knees to beg his Life of us, but we were forced to ſacrifice it to our own ſafety. After we were rid of all our Enemies we returned to the Sea ſide, and gave <hi>Alvarez</hi> the Signal which we had agreed upon, being a Handkerchief held up upon the end of a Stick; he anſwered it by a Broad-ſide upon a Ship of the contrary Party, which was next to him, and his example was followed by <hi>Ablington,</hi> and by <hi>Velaſquez</hi> his Lieutenant. The
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59690:49"/>Night was ſo dark, and the ſmoak of the Cannon ſo thick, that we could not ſee any thing more. A little while after the Clouds, with which the Heavens were covered, broke with ſo terrible a Noiſe, and the Rain fell in ſo great abundance, that we were forced to ſeek for ſhelter in this Rock, although the Thunder and the Lightning, which frightned us, had nothing in them but what was Natural, we thought that the Heavens, diſpleaſed with our having ſo lately ſpilt ſo much Blood, had ſent this Tempeſt, as a mark of its Anger. When the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der had ceaſed chiding for a while, the Waves beat againſt each other with ſo much violence, and were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſuch a height, that we thought they were juſt going to overwhelm us; the Winds which were ſhut up in this Rock, made ſuch terrible Ecchoes, that we feared, every minute, we ſhould be buried under its Ruines. I had not Courage enough to reſiſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59690:50"/>ſo many Alarms, and I ſell into a Swoon, out of which I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the Lamentations of <hi>Velaſquez.</hi> He had been out, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout day-break, towards the Sea-ſide, where he ſaw the Wracks of three of the Ships of <hi>Winch</hi> his Fleet, which had ſuffered Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack againſt this Rock. The vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Tempeſt had carried from the Shore the Bodies that were drowned, and there appearing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pieces of Maſts, Boards, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heavy things, which were more capable of reſiſting the Waves, <hi>Velaſquez</hi> could not judge of which ſide thoſe were that had ſuffered Shipwrack; however, in this doubt, he could not avoid ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſurprize vvith continual La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, which vvere ſo loud, that they came to my Ears. I aroſe immediately, and ran tovvards the place vvhere I heard his voice, to knovv vvhat nevv Misfortunes vve vvere expoſed to; he ſhevved
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59690:50"/>me the ſubject of his Complaints; and the Sea being calm, I looked out on all ſides, to ſee if I could diſcover any of the Veſſels of our Friends, but I ſaw nothing but the ſad Wracks which <hi>Velaſquez</hi> had ſhewed me at firſt; I thought that I had no more reaſon to doubt but that the Fleet was loſt, and that the Anger of Heaven had puniſhed the Innocent with the Guilty. The fear with which I was ſeized, at this cruel reflection, made me fall again into my firſt ſort of Indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> who ſaw me ſtagger, came forwards to ſupport me, and having made his Servants bring ſome water, he threw it in my Face, to make me come to my ſelf; he made me ſit down upon a bundle of Sea-weeds, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving me to open my Eyes, he endeavour'd to perſuade me (to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate my Fears,) that Heaven was too juſt, to have preſerved an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Pyrate, rather than thoſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59690:51"/>who had taken upon them the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of oppreſt Virtue; he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, that, before Night, we ſhould ſee the three Veſſels, which cauſed our Fears, come back again to take us up, that we might continue our Voyage. He told me, that if we ſtayed any longer without having any news of them, we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they were forced into ſome Neighbouring Port, to repair the dammages they ſuſtained by this laſt ſtorm. As we are apt to believe what we deſire, the reaſons which <hi>Velaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> urged quieted a little my mind; but when we had ſtayed three days, and I found that our Victuals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow ſhort, and that we had no news, either of <hi>Alvarez</hi> or <hi>Ablington,</hi> I relapſed into my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer melancholy. We reſolved to get up to the top of the Mountain, to ſeek after ſome inhabited place; and we left one of our Servants at the Sea-ſide, to deſire our Friends to ſtay for us there, if they ſhould
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59690:51"/>come to Land in that place. We went about the Rock, but we found it ſo ſteep, that it was impoſſible for us to get up to the top; and after having wearied our ſelves, without ſucceſs, for ſeveral hours, we were forced to return back to the place from whence we came. We ſtayed there two days, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any hopes of an end of our Afflictions; we began to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves for Death, as a thing we were certain of. We were ſo wearied with diſcovering the Country, that notwithſtanding our deſperate Condition, we ſlept as ſoundly, as if we had had in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance all things neceſſary for Life. I was the firſt up in the morning, riſing at break of day, and uſing my uſual Exerciſe, I went to the Sea-ſide. After having walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all ſides, and looked about, to find with my doubting Eyes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, which did not come, I would have returned back the ſame way I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59690:52"/>came, but I was ſeized with fear, at the ſight of a terrible Lyon, which came towards me. I cryed out aloud, which brought <hi>Velaſquez</hi> to my help. One would have thought this Beaſt had been ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my Fear; he appeared to me ſo gentle and loving. He let fall at my Feet a wild Kid, which he brought in his Mouth, and rolling himſelf upon the Sand, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited me, by this action, to come to ſtroak him: I was ſo afrighted, that, far from going to him, I could not ſtand upon my Legs. My Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, who was bolder than I, and as he was as willing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the Lyon, as to dye with Hunger, he made a ſign to one of his Servants, to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Prey, whilſt he ſhould play with the Lyon. He went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this furious Animal, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ventured ſeveral times to ſtroak his ſides with his hands, he found him ſo tame, that he became
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59690:52"/>bolder, and put his Hand in his Mouth, and plaid with him, as if he had been a little Lap Dog. But when he ſaw his Servant had hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his theft, he made an end of his dangerous Play, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Lyon, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned ſoftly back the ſame way by which he came.</p>
                  <p>When we had loſt ſight of the Lyon, we cut down ſome Boughs from the Trees, the dryeſt we could find, and having lighted a Fire with two Flints, upon a heap of dryed Leaves, we dreſt, after the faſhion of the Country, the Veniſon, which the Noble Beaſt had hunted, and had been cut up by our Servants. Hunger made us reliſh this Meat more deliciouſly than any we had ever been at, and we only wiſhed that the Lyon would continue to be our Purvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. Our Hopes were not deceived, this tractable Beaſt, which ſaw himſelf Careſſed, uſed himſelf to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59690:53"/>viſit us often, and took care to feed us with what his Chace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. When we found, by theſe means, our ſubſiſtence was ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, we thought of nothing, but finding a way to get out of the place where we were, by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lyon, which we looked upon as ſent by Heaven for our ſupport. We ſuppoſed there was ſome Habitation upon the Hill, where the Man lived who had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this Lyon, and that he would have been more wild, had he been bred up in the Woods. Upon this aſſurance we reſolved to make him our Guide. <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> who had more Strength and Activity than I had, undertook the Enterpriſe. The next day the Lyon being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from hunting, <hi>Velaſquez</hi> took his Sword and a Gun, which he had brought out of the Ship, and followed him afar off. The Lyon climbed up the Rock, and going through ſo many difficult
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59690:53"/>ways, that <hi>Velaſquez</hi> was forced to make uſe of his hands, to keep himſelf from falling. And after having often gone up and come down the Rock, he at length diſcover'd the higheſt point of it. He had not far to go to the top of the Rock, when the Lyon having rouzed a Deer of that Country, ſomewhat different from thoſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> began to run after him with ſo great a ſwiftneſs, that <hi>Velaſquez</hi> could not follow him. The trouble which this was to him, did not laſt long, for his guide having caught his Prey, walked gently before him with it, and gave him time to follow him to the top of the Hill. <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> who found himſelf weary, had a mind to take Breath a little, and turning himſelf towards the Sea, he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſo great a Tract of Land, that he could not forbear fixing his Eyes, and conſidering it exactly. In the mean vvhile the Lyon continued on his vvay; and vvhen <hi>Velaſquez</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:59690:54"/>vvould have follovved him, he no more knevv vvhat vvas become of him. He ran to overtake him, but ſtumbling fell dovvn. His Gun, which he held cockt in his Hand, that it might be the readier for uſe, if there vvere occaſion, vvent off at the ſame time. The Old Man, vvho inhabits the Grotto vvhere you found me, ſurprized vvith hearing the noiſe of a Gun in that ſolitary place, came out, follovved by the Lyon. So ſoon as he ſavv <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> he came tovvards him, and offered him his aſſiſtance in <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Companion extreamly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced to find, in ſuch a Deſart, a Man vvho underſtood his Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, related to him in a fevv vvords the adventure vvhich had brought him into this place, and told him he had left me with two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants on the Sea ſide. They came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to take us vvith them, by a much eaſier vvay, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59690:54"/>ſide of the Mountain: but it ending a great vvay from the place vvhere vve vvere, vve vvere forced to turn about the Cape in a Boat, vvhich the Old Man uſed for Fiſhing. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſquez</hi> asked, in his vvalk vvith the Old Man, vvhy the Lyon took another Path, than that vvhich vve follovved to go to the Sea? To vvhich he anſvvered, That the Lyon, in hunting, ſought after places vvhich vvere leaſt frequented. I began to fear ſome accident had happened to <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> vvhen I ſavv the Boat come to the place vvhere vve vvere. I went on Board vvith an unconceivable Joy, but it vvas much greater, vvhen the Old Man told me vve vvere in the Kingdom of <hi>Chilli,</hi> and not far from the Tovvn of <hi>Penco.</hi> Being extreamly tired, and in a very bad Equipage, I deſired <hi>Velaſquez</hi> to ſeek my Father,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59690:55"/>taking his tvvo Servants vvith him, and come to me again vvhere I vvas, vvith Cloaths, Horſes, and Arms; but the nevvs vvhich you have brought me of the loſs of the Battel, makes me fear he is fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Enemy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Garcia</hi> thus finiſhed his Relation; and although <hi>Don Henriquez</hi> had hearkened to it, as a pleaſant Fable, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance he had for the fair diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed Perſon, prevailed vvith him not to diſcover his thoughts. And he alſo found ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for him in doubting of his Sex, ſince under the notion of a Brother he might take Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties vvhich vvere not allovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, vvere the Sex of <hi>Don Garcia</hi> knovvn. He expreſſed by the moſt tender tranſports, the Joy vvhich he had for ſo happy a meeting; but it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing late he vvas forced to go
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59690:55"/>into the Cave vvith him, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake that nouriſhment vvhich muſt not be refuſed to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:59690:56"/>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:59690:56"/>
               <head>DON HENRIQUES DE CASTRO.</head>
               <head>Book II.</head>
               <p>AFter the two Brothers had dined, they thought they could not ſpend the day better, than in ſeeing the Lyon Hunt. <hi>Don Henriquez,</hi> who loved this exerciſe very well, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, as well as his ſtrength would give him leave. But <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> or rather, Princeſs <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> for ſo it was in reality, being more tender, ſtayed in the Wood,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59690:57"/>which was upon the ſide of the Hill. A Fountain which precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it felf from the top of the Rock, formed many Caſcades, and made that place very fit to muſe in; ſhe promiſed her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to wait for him there, but when he was gone out of ſight, ſhe took the way towards <hi>Penco,</hi> thinking ſhe could not with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency ſtay with a Man who had given ſo many inſtances to her of a violent Paſſion. Altho' he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan not to be indifferent to her, yet her Vertue made her renounce the Pleaſure, which ſhe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from his Converſation. She took the way towards the Sea, that ſhe might put her ſelf in the Old Man's Boat, and follow the Shore. She thought that thereby ſhe would be leaſt expoſed to the meeting either of <hi>Indians</hi> or the wild Beaſts, and ſhe made ſo much haſte, that ſhe was very ſoon at the bottom of the Rock.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:59690:57"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Henriquez,</hi> who had not had any ſuſpicion of her deſign, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to the Wood, where he had left her, ſo ſoon as he had ended his Chaſe; his mind full of the tender thoughts, with which his Paſſion inſpir'd him. When he miſſed her, he accuſed himſelf of neglect, for having abandoned her in ſo wild a place, where ſhe was expoſed to a thouſand Dangers. A moment afterwards, he reproched himſelf for having diſcovered to her his Paſſion, before he had ſought for the ways of pleaſing her; and he feared he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained her to go from him, by reaſon of his too precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Declarations. But upon the whole matter, he did not know what to think of it, ſometimes he thought ſhe was become a Prey to the wild Beaſts, wherewith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe Mountains were filled; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother time he fancied ſhe had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooked for another retreat, to keep
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59690:58"/>a decency, and not to expoſe her Honour. Sometimes he blamed his own levity, and the eaſineſs with which he had forgotten <hi>Leonora,</hi> to love the next Object, which preſented it ſelf to his Eyes. From this thought, he ran to another, and took the meeting of the tame Lyon, and of the young Beauty which had charm'd him, all for a Deluſion. <q>
                     <hi>It may be,</hi> ſaid he to himſelf, <hi>it is the Spirit of</hi> Leonora, <hi>who had a mind to put thy Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to this Tryal, and her ſudden retreat is a convincing proof of it. Thou didſt not ſay any thing to this Fair Stranger, which could affright her, and what could make her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, thou ſhould'ſt ever ſail in thy reſpect to her? And ſince ſhe had no reaſon to leave thee, it is to be preſumed, it could be nothing but an Apparition; ſo fearful as ſhe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be, certainly ſhe would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have undertaken a Journey thus alone, in an unknown Countrey. She
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59690:58"/>would rather have ſtayed with me, than expoſe her ſelf to unavoidable dangers, by flying from me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou canſt not but think that it is the Ghoſt of a dead</hi> Leonora, <hi>and dead, becauſe ſhe would have given her ſelf to thee, and which will eternally haunt thy ſteps, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thy unfaithfulneſs.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Henriques</hi> was not ſo poſſeſt with this thought, but he had a remainder of hope, which made him ſearch for her in all the places where he thought he might find her. He ſpent ſo much time in this, that it was far in the Night before he came into the <hi>Grotto.</hi> He was amazed to meet there the old Man, who had dwelt there with a Lady of a great Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, although ſhe was not very young. She was dreſt after the Spaniſh faſhion, as alſo a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who accompanied her, and ſhe had almoſt all the Features of the Counterfeit <hi>Don Garcia,</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59690:59"/>which increaſed the ſurprize of <hi>Don Henriquez.</hi> However he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted the Company, with a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of mind, which ſhewed the greatneſs of his Birth. He Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented the Maſter of this Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, with an excuſe for having, in his abſence, taken up his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he told him that he had done it by the encouragement of <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> who had aſſured him, that he would not take it ill, that he had uſed this liberty, but that he was very much aſhamed to come back without that dear Friend, who had promiſed to make his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes for him. At the naming of <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> the Lady, in a paſſion, could not forbear interrupting <hi>Don Henriquez,</hi> to ask him what was become of that Traytor, and what he had done with her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <q>
                     <hi>Madam,</hi> replied this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>if ſhe be in the power of</hi> Don Garcia, <hi>you need not fear any thing for her Honour. I know very well
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59690:59"/>that there is no body, who may not be deceived by him, and who would not truſt his diſcretion. It is not that which I mean,</hi> replied Don Henriquez, <hi>but that ſhe is a Lady, diſguiſed in the habit of a Man, and that therefore your Daughter is in great ſecurity with her.</hi>
                  </q> This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe increaſing the wonder of the Lady, the Company deſired <hi>Don Henriquez</hi> to relate what had paſſed between <hi>Don Garcia</hi> and him, and what he had learnt of the Hiſtory of his Life; he gave imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately this ſatisfaction to the ſtrange Lady, but ſhe could find no eaſe by it. <hi>Don Henriquez,</hi> for his part, had not leſs impatience, to diſcourſe in private with the old Man, and to know from him who that <hi>Julia</hi> was who ſo perfectly reſembled <hi>Leonora.</hi> So ſoon as it was day, he engaged him to walk with him, and having ſhewed him her Picture, he asked him if he there diſcovered the Features of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59690:60"/>
                  <hi>Julia;</hi> after the old Man had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him that it was the true Picture, he asked him by what accident he had loſt her. <q>
                     <hi>I cannot,</hi> replied the <hi>Stranger, ſatisfie your curioſity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out opening again a wound which has bled for a long time, but which now begins to cloſe; but if it be any ſervice to you, I will endeavour to overcome my grief, to relate to you the accidents with which my life has been croſt.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Don Henriquez</hi> told him it was very important for his qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, to hear this relation, and having conducted him into a private place, that they might not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, he made him ſit down in the ſhade, and deſired him to ſatisfie his Curioſity, which he did in this manner.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:59690:60"/>
                  <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Don Eſtevan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I am called <hi>Don Eſtevan de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro. What,</hi> interruped Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riquez, <hi>are you the Father of</hi> Don Lorenzo, <hi>who was thought to have died in Priſon at</hi> Tunis? I am he, <hi>replied Don Eſtevan,</hi> Fortune which reſerved me for other Croſſes, reſcued me from Slavery, to make my ſufferings the more laſting. <hi>And I,</hi> replied Don Henriquez, <hi>am the Son of the ſame</hi> Don Lorenzo, <hi>and of</hi> Tereſamendez. I had, <hi>repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Don Eſtevan,</hi> ſome ſuſpition of it before, for I obſerved his very Features in you; and <hi>Mendez,</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to your Mother, who was in my <hi>Grotto</hi> when you came thither, had the ſame thought; for this reaſon, I was not willing to refuſe you a confidence, which may
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59690:61"/>give you ſome ſatisfaction; and I will continue my relation, if you are diſpoſed to hear me; and, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Don Heriquez</hi> kept ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, he thus purſued his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>I believe, Son, you are not ignorant of the reaſons which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to leave my Countrey and have made me, for fifteen years laſt paſt, wander from King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to Kingdom? <q>
                        <hi>Yes, my Lord,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Don Henriquez, <hi>I know that</hi> Don John de Fonſeca <hi>was in love with your firſt Wife, and that, not being able to obtain his deſires, he was reſolved to be revenged of her, and of</hi> Don Lopes de la Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae, <hi>who had had better ſucceſs with his own Wife, that to bring about this deſign, he had made you be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by a Maid, who was gained by him, that</hi> Lopes <hi>kept with your Wife a Correſpondence which was prejudicial to your Honour; that you having in Friendſhip told him of it,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59690:61"/>he confirmed you himſelf in theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions, and promiſed you he would ſo order it, that you ſhould find them together at their firſt meeting: That to effect this treachery, he told his Wife, that yours had talked every where in publick, that</hi> Don Lopes <hi>bragged of the favours he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from her, and that ſhe was deſirous to Juſtifie her ſelf in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in the Houſe of a Sempſtreſs, who was one of their Confidents; that</hi> Don John, <hi>who knew the Hour they pitcht upon, went with you thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made you come in at one door, whilſt his Wife went out at the other; that your Wife being come thither to clear her ſelf, was, by theſe means, left alone with</hi> Don Lopes; <hi>and that finding them together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any body with them, you were fully perſwaded ſhe had betrayed you: and being tranſported at it, with jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie you killed them both, him with your Piſtol, and her with your Sword; and that thinking, after having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59690:62"/>theſe murthers, you could not expect any ſafety in</hi> Sevil, <hi>you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thence immediately. I know but confuſedly, all that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to you afterwards, becauſe you changed your Name, that you might not be known.</hi>
                     </q> You have done me a great pleaſure, <hi>replied Don Eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> to ſpare me the confuſion I ſhould have been in; if I had been forced to relate to you my ſelf, the Crime which my Credulity made me commit, with too much precipitancy; but ſince you are ſo well informed of theſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I have nothing more to tell you, but what happened to me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I left <hi>Sevil.</hi> I went from <hi>Sevil</hi> to <hi>Seragoſſa,</hi> where <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Iſabella</hi> then kept their Court. It was eaſie for me to hide my ſelf in the throng of Strangers, who came thither from all parts, but fearing I might at leſt be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, I reſolved to go into ſome other Countrey, to ſerve in the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59690:62"/>Army. I heard <hi>Charles</hi> the VIII of <hi>France,</hi> was then deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Italy</hi> with a ſtrong Army, to recover the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> which he pretended belonged to him, as deſcended from the Houſe of <hi>Anjou,</hi> from which it had been unjuſtly taken away by Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They told me alſo that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> took no part in this War, which made me reſolve to ſerve in the <hi>French</hi> Army, rather than in that of <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> who was not now in a condition to reſiſt ſo great a Monarch. I took Poſt immediately, and having croſſed the <hi>Pyrenian</hi> Hills, I came to <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> where was appointed the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rendezvous of the Army; I found the King ready to paſs the <hi>Alpes;</hi> and having no Acquaintance in <hi>France,</hi> I followed the Army in the quality of a Volunteer. I had a pretty handſome Equipage, and ſpending liberally, I ſoon got Friends in the Army. We paſſed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59690:63"/>through <hi>Italy,</hi> as if the King had only travelled through his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; ſo great a Veneration had all the little Soveraigns of the Countreys, where we paſſed, for this Prince. When we were come to the frontiers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples,</hi> we heard that <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> frightned by the approach of our Army, was retired to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zara</hi> in <hi>Scicily,</hi> where he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Monk; his Son <hi>Ferdinand</hi> indeavoured to make ſome reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but ſeeing all places open their Gates to the <hi>French,</hi> without ſtaying for their Cannon, he feared leſt his own Subjects ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him up to King <hi>Charles,</hi> and therefore retired into the Iſland of <hi>Chio,</hi> leaving us, by his retreat, maſters of his Kingdom. <hi>Charles</hi> made himſelf be Crowned King of this new Conqueſt, and after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left there a Vice-Roy, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in order to his return for <hi>France;</hi> and it was, to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59690:63"/>in this Voyage that we began to make War.</p>
                  <p>Theſe great ſucceſſes of <hi>Charles</hi> had allarmed all the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> who being leagued together, raiſed a great Army under the Conduct of <hi>Francis de Gonzaga.</hi> This great General diſputed with us the paſſage of the <hi>Texin,</hi> and we were forced to come to blows. I was ſo happy in this fight, as to ſave the life of the Marſhal <hi>de Gie,</hi> who commanded our Van-Guard; his Horſe having been killed under him, I gave him mine, and after having diſmounted with a blow of my Sword, a Horſeman, who had his Sword at the Marſhals back, mounted upon his Horſe; the Marſhal was ſo thankful to me for this Service, that he would not ſuffer me to make uſe of any other Table but his, and lodged me in his Houſe, when I came to <hi>Paris.</hi> He had a Nephew in his Houſe, called <hi>Keroline,</hi> with whom
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59690:64"/>I contracted a ſtrict Friendſhip; and the chief employment of the <hi>French,</hi> being to viſit the Ladies in time of peace, I accompanied him in a viſit he made to a Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Candale,</hi> for whom the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> had a great paſſion; this Lady, whom I had the honour to pleaſe, introduced me into that Princes ſervice, whoſe Favourite I became ſoon after; few days after this, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Beaujeu,</hi> whom the Duke courted to marry, having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered this Intreague, became jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of it, and complained to the King, who ſent my Maſter Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to the Tower of <hi>Bourges.</hi> I remained ſome time at <hi>Paris,</hi> for my Maſter's ſervice, but having heard that <hi>Keroline</hi> reported every where, that my indiſcretion had been the cauſe of the Duke's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; I could not avoid challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and fighting him; we fought with Sword and Daggar
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59690:64"/>upon the Road to the <hi>Bois de Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;</hi> many of our Friends ran after us to part us, but they came too late, for our Combat was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the death of <hi>Keroline.</hi> And Duels being forbidden then in <hi>France,</hi> the fear I had of being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner, made me, without delay, take Poſt for <hi>Lyons,</hi> and then repaſſed the <hi>Alpes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I heard, at <hi>Turin,</hi> that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was come back into his Dominions, that King <hi>Charles</hi> was dead, that my Maſter had ſucceeded him, by the name of <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, and that he had entered into a League with <hi>Spain</hi> for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Milan,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Naples.</hi> Although I had a great deal to hope for in <hi>France,</hi> from the goodneſs of the new King, who had been ſo kind to me when I ſerved hm, yet the love of my Countrey made me reſolve to take a Command in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, ſo ſoon as it was
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59690:65"/>raiſed. I came thither in all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and I waited upon <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand Gonzalez de Cordoua</hi> Marqueſs <hi>de Leve,</hi> who commanded it, he had heard of me to my advantage, when I went by the name of <hi>Demiguel Cardegnas,</hi> which I had taken in <hi>France;</hi> this induced him to make me Lieutenant of his own Lances.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ferdinand</hi> having been a ſecond time Stript of his Countrey, the two Kings quarrelled about the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of their Conqueſt, and I was forced to bear Arms againſt the <hi>French,</hi> at the Battel which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Leve</hi> fought aginſt the Duke of <hi>Nemours.</hi> I took ſeveral Priſoners in this fight, and amongſt others <hi>Bleſſac,</hi> who was a near Kinſman to the Lady that had given me to the Duke of <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> he made himſelf known to me, and being very glad to have this opportunity, to acknowledge the favours I had received from
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59690:65"/>his Kinſwoman, I ſent him back without ranſom, which afterwards ſaved my life, as I ſhall tell you. I was taken at the Battel which the <hi>French</hi> won neer <hi>Ravenna,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of <hi>Gaſton de Foix,</hi> and being ſo unhappy as to render my ſelf to <hi>Keroline</hi>'s Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he would have killed me, to revenge the death of a Man I had killed without treachery; but <hi>Bleſſac,</hi> who was preſent, could not ſuffer ſo great a baſeneſs, he took my part with ſo much warmth that it came to blows, and they fought at the head of the Camp; this quarrel happenning in the preſence of ſo many, they were ſoon parted; but however in this diſturbance, I found an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to eſcape; I got back to <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna,</hi> whither the remaining part of our Army had retreated, where I remained ſick for many Months; for the wounds which I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the laſt fight, having
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59690:66"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:59690:66"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:59690:67"/>been long without dreſſing, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed and put me into a Feaver, and out of which, I recovered with great difficulty. a <hi>Spaniard</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> who had been my deareſt Neighbour when I lived at <hi>Sevil,</hi> lodged in the ſame Houſe where I lay ſick. he came by chance into my Chamber, and knew me, although I was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much altered; he offered me his ſervice with ſo good a Grace, that I ſpoke to him without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, I enquired of him, what had paſſed ſince my departure; and he informed me, that my Son, who was but four years of age, when I was forced to leave my Countrey; and who is the ſame <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> whoſe Son you are, was gone into the <hi>Indies</hi> with <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando Cortez,</hi> he told me alſo, that although he was very young, yet he had gained a great Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was a great comfort to me.</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:59690:67"/>
                  <p>The Wars of <hi>Italy</hi> being ended by the loſs of the Battel of <hi>Pavie,</hi> and by the Impriſonment of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>France,</hi> who had ſucceeded <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, I found my ſelf without employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not daring to return into <hi>Spain,</hi> I reſolved to go to <hi>Naples,</hi> to paſs my time there, till a new War ſhould find me an employment. I had done great ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the laſt time this Town was taken, to <hi>Alexander Cappaccio,</hi> who made there a conſiderable Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and although he was ſince dead, his Wife did not forget it. I went to give her a viſit, and ſhe would not ſuffer me to lodge in any other Houſe but hers; ſhe had with her a Daughter, who was the only fruit of her mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. <hi>Flavia,</hi> for ſo ſhe was called, was grown as much in Beauty, as in Age, ſince I ſaw her, and her Charms raiſed jealouſie in the greateſt Beauties of <hi>Naples;</hi> her
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59690:68"/>Lovers were in great number; but in that Crowd, ſhe had caſt her Eye more eſpecially upon two Brothers, who were no leſs conſiderable for their Merit, than their Birth; the name of the Eldeſt was <hi>Scipio,</hi> and the Youngeſt <hi>Octavius;</hi> there was ſo great an equality between them, that <hi>Flavia</hi> durſt not chuſe the one, for fear of diſpleaſing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I having the opportunity to ſee her at all hours, ſhe told me her thoughts with great freedom. One day, after having related to me, what theſe two Brothers had done to deſerve her kindneſs, and having deſcribed to me the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of each, ſhe asked my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, concerning the choice ſhe was to make. I anſwered her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, to make them agree, her beſt way was to give me a Heart, for which theſe two Rivals diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſo much heat, to hinder Love from diſtinguiſhing in them the Sentiments of Nature. She look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59690:68"/>upon me ſmilingly, and ſeeing in my eyes an amorous languiſhing, which ſhe had never before obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhe began to think I ſpoke this only to diſcover her thoughts. My humour was not unpleaſing to her, and ſhe found in the advice, which I gave her, ſomething which flattered her Inclination, but ſhe would not let me know what paſſed in her Heart, until ſhe had ſatisfied her ſelf better, what I ſelf for her: ſhe obſerved my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour with great exactneſs, and ſo ſoon as ſhe was fully perſwaded of the truth of my Paſſion, ſhe began to love the two Brothers leſs; they ſoon were ſenſible of her coldneſs towards them, and ſeeing ſhe favoured none of their Rivals, they gueſſed I was the cauſe of this change in her. You know, that in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Women have not any more liberty than in <hi>Spain,</hi> and that the greateſt favour they can afford to their Lovers,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59690:69"/>is to appear at a Window, or in a Balcony, when they give them a Serenade, and make Love to them. <hi>Flavia</hi> ſhewed this Complaiſance to none but the two Brothers; and therefore it was eaſie for them to gueſs, that if ſhe had any other Amour, it muſt be with me, whom ſhe might ſee at all times, ſince I lodged in the Houſe. They did not dare to make their jealouſie known to me, for fear of diſpleaſing their Miſtreſs, or her Mother. But <hi>Scipio,</hi> who was the violenteſt of the two, ingaged me to play with him, and having picked a quarrel with me, he provoked me to ſuch a Degree, that I was forced to draw my Sword upon him, we went to fight out of the Town, and he attacqued me with ſo much violence, that he run himſelf through with my Sword, and fell down dead at my feet. The Officer who was guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome Priſoners to <hi>Naples,</hi> being followed by about twenty Guards,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59690:69"/>paſſed by the place where we had fought, and having ſeized me, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me away to Priſon. <hi>Flavia</hi> heard with great trouble, the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune which had befallen me, and ſhe having been the innocent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it, ſhe ſent for <hi>Don Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> to find out with him ſome way to ſave me. He adviſed her, to make uſe of the Power ſhe had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Octavius,</hi> and to ingage him to let fall his proſecution. She imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately took a Pen in her hand, and writ to him in theſe words.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> are not ignorant of the Intereſt I ought to take in whatſoever concerns <hi>Don Miguel de Cardegnas,</hi> I cannot abandon him without Ingratitude, after the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices he has done for our Family. You have taken the Tokens of my acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, for the effects of a more tender Paſſion; and your Brother loſt himſelf, by not having known my thoughts well. I am willing to help
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59690:70"/>you out of an Error, by ingageing to you my Faith, and and I ſhall do it without repugnancy; ſince your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is dead, nothing hinders me from yielding up my ſelf wholy to you. But to obtain this Happineſs, you muſt ſacrifice all your reſentments, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore <hi>Don Miguel</hi> his Liberty. And you have no reaſon to hate a Man, who by taking from you a Brother, at the ſame time freed you of a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val. Therefore never ſee me again, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you bring him back with you, and ſatisfie your ſelf; my Heart and my Hand are only to be had at this Price.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>She immediately ſent this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Octavius,</hi> who, to ſhew the ſtrength of his Love, by the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his obedience, went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the Judges, who had condemned him. He told them he knew my Innocency, and deſired them to let me be freed out of Priſon. They anſwered him, that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59690:70"/>the time was now paſt, and that the Sentence having been once gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there was no way to revoke it. <hi>Octavius,</hi> who feared <hi>Flavia</hi> would accuſe him of negligence, reſolved to reſcue me, when they carried me to Execution. He got his Friends together, and having poſted them in the <hi>Avenues,</hi> where I was to paſs, ſo ſoon as he ſaw me appear, he fell upon the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers who guarded me, with ſo much violence, that they were forced to quit me. And he came immediately and unbound me. But as I was giving him my thanks for ſo generous an Action, the Guards, who were already gone a conſiberable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from us, fired in their flight upon us, to hide their Cowardiſe. And <hi>Octavius</hi> was ſo unfortunate, that a Bullet, which was ſhot at random, hit him in the Head, and mortally wounded him; when I ſaw my help was of no uſe to my Benefactor, I thought of nothing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59690:71"/>but making my eſcape in this diſturbance, and being paſſed the Gates of the City, I retired to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua. Don Alvarez</hi> took care to let me hear from <hi>Flavia</hi> every day. He ſent me word, that the Mother of <hi>Flavia,</hi> taking me for a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Fortune, had condemned the Inclination that fair Perſon had for me, and had forbidden her to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a Commerce, whereof ſhe diſapproved ſo much. I deſired <hi>Don Alvarez</hi> to tell her my true Name, without telling her the reaſons which had made me change it, and to diſpoſe her to give me her Daughter, ſhewing her that my Birth was not inferior to hers. My Friend acquitted himſelf of this Commiſſion, with a great deal of Wit. But this Lady intending to write into <hi>Spain,</hi> to be aſſured that what he had told her was true; he feared the cruel Adventures which happened to me at <hi>Sevil,</hi> would be known to her. <hi>Flavia,</hi> who
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59690:71"/>was afraid her Mother ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage her to any body elſe, and marry her againſt her Inclination, reſolved to come to me to <hi>Capua,</hi> and be married to me there pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, ſhe diſcovered her Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> who ſent to me to come incognito to <hi>Naples.</hi> So ſoon as I was arrived there, he gave notice of it to <hi>Flavia,</hi> who came out of her Lodgings in the dusk of the Evening, at the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Door, where I waited for her, with my Friend. We led her into a Houſe which was not far from thence, where vve remained con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed for five or ſix days. When vve found that the noiſe of the ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling avvay of <hi>Flavia</hi> vvhich vvas ſpread about the Tovvn, vvas ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat abated, vve returned to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua,</hi> vvhere <hi>I</hi> married <hi>Flavia</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately. I then made my Friends uſe their Endeavours with her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they convinced her ſo fully, that I vvas not a Match un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthy
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59690:72"/>of her, that at length ſhe approved of our Marriage, and came to take us up at <hi>Capua,</hi> to bring us to a fine Houſe vvhich ſhe had in <hi>Calabria</hi> on the Sea ſide.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Don Eſtevan</hi> was continuing his Relation, when he was interrupted by the Arrival of <hi>Mendez</hi> and the unknown Lady, who not having found them in the Cave, came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſeek them. The old Man told them he had diſcovered that <hi>Don Henriquez</hi> vvas his Grandſon, and Son to <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> of vvhom he had ſo often ſpoken to him. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the tvvo nevv Comers vvere ſeated near <hi>Don Henriquez</hi> and the Old Man, the ſtrange <hi>Lady</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted <hi>Mendez,</hi> for his being alvvays in ſo deep a ſtudy. <q>
                        <hi>Well Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>does the remembrance of the Princeſs</hi> Zulemaide <hi>poſſeſs always your mind, and are you reſolved to leave us, to ſeek her, without knowing in what part of the World you can find
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59690:72"/>her? I confeſs Madam,</hi> replied Mendez, <hi>that ſince I loſt her, I have never had a moment of quiet, and that I have wandered from one Pole to the other, for ſome years paſt, without diſcovering what might give me any hopes of ſeeing any period put to my misfortunes; but only that which the Man of the Houſe, where we lodged at</hi> Penco, <hi>told me; who gave me ſome Idea of the Courſe I ought to take, to ſucceed in an undertaking, which has hitherto been without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>Don Henriquez,</hi> having heard nothing of the Adventures vvhich had happened to <hi>Mendez,</hi> and that all that vvas now ſpoken concerning Princeſs <hi>Zulemaide</hi> vvas a Riddle to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he deſired his Unkle to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain it to him. <hi>Don Eſtevan</hi> and the ſtrange Lady, joined in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of <hi>Don Henriques,</hi> all three preſſing him ſo hard to afford them this ſatisfaction, that he could not refuſe it; and, having ſtudied a little while, he began his Relation in theſe words.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:59690:73"/>
                  <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Mendez</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaide.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>YOU have been informed of my Birth, and knowing as you do, that War has been for a long time my employment; I have nothing to relate to you, of the firſt Accidents of my Youth. I was at <hi>Diu,</hi> when <hi>Ruſtan-Baſha</hi> came to beſiege it by order from <hi>Soliman</hi> the Emperor of the <hi>Turks. Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro de Sylvera,</hi> who was Governour of it, ſent me into <hi>Peru,</hi> to demand Succours from <hi>Pizarro.</hi> A ſtorm drives me upon a Deſart Iſland, which is not far diſtant from the Province of <hi>Cuſco,</hi> and the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and mildneſs of the Climate, invited me to Land there. I for ſome time admired the Beauty of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59690:73"/>the Countrey, but after having walked in it a quarter of an Hour, I met with what ſtruck me with admiration, I ſaw between the Trees a young Woman, naked, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixteen years old, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully beautiful. Altho' ſhe was very much amazed to ſee me, yet ſhe did not run away, but gave me leave to come nearer to her. I ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her in <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> if ſhe would come into my Ship, but ſhe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me with an inarticulated Voice, which reſembled more the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Beaſts, than a human voice. I made her obſerve the Ship which I came in, and made her under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by ſigns, the Propoſition I had made to her. She reached out her hand to me, and ſuffered me without difficulty, to lead her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Ship. The Storm being cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I continued my Courſe, and arrived in a ſhort time in <hi>Peru.</hi> I went to <hi>Pizarro,</hi> and carried with me this young Woman, to whom
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59690:74"/>I had given one of my Suits of Cloaths to cover her nakedneſs, until I had time to have ſome made, conformable to her Sex. She had a very lively wit, and altho' our voyage was very ſhort, yet I taught her <hi>Portugueſe</hi> enough in that time, to make her ſelf underſtood. When I had brought her up to be fit to converſe with, I asked her how ſhe came to be left in this uninhabited Iſland, and naked. <q>
                        <hi>Seigneur,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I had always been ſhut up in a Cave, out of which I could not ſtir, the entry being cloſed by great Thorns, ſome great Beaſts, which I think they call Lyons, brought me what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for my nouriſhment, till about three Months ago, a Thunderclap broke the top of the Cavern where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was ſhut; and I was ſurprized to ſee the light. I obſerved very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly the circuit of this Cave, and finding Stones which came forwarder ſome than others, and which I might make uſe of for ſteps, to get to the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59690:74"/>top of the Vault, and to get out of my Priſon. I put my ſelf in a poſture of executing this thought, I found the execution of it ſo eaſie, that in a little time, I ſet my ſelf at full liberty. I went round the Iſland ſeveral times, to find out, if I could, any Creature which reſembled me, that I might converſe with him, but having found there no habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor a poſſibility to look for any further, I contented my ſelf, with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the fruits which the Iſland af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me, without extending my curioſity further. When I ſaw you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon the top of the Hill, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined you narrowly, and ſeeing you were made very like me, excepting your being clothed, and I being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, I ſtayed till you came up, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being frightned, to learn what it was you came to ſeek in this Iſland.</hi>
                     </q> When ſhe had done ſpeaking, I asked her many queſtions, that I might know by what accident ſhe came to be ſhut up in this Cave,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59690:75"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:59690:75"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:59690:76"/>but I could learn nothing more of it from her.</p>
                  <p>When I was arrived at the Camp of <hi>Pizarro,</hi> they would have impriſoned me as a Spye, becauſe they ſaid I had with me in mans Cloaths, <hi>Rominagui</hi>'s Wife, who was Daughter to the late King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabalipa;</hi> but after they had look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon her more attentively, (the Perſon they took for this Princeſs,) they found ſhe was much younger, and much more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, which made them ceaſe to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me from delivering to <hi>Pizar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> the Pacquet wherewith <hi>Don Pedro de Silvera</hi> had intruſted me for him. I had a very obliging re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from him, but he gave me to underſtand, that he had need himſelf of his Forces, that he could not ſend any of them to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of <hi>Diu.</hi> During the ſtay which I made in the Army, I learnt the Queen of <hi>Peru</hi> was ready to be brought to Bed, when <hi>Pizarro</hi> took
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59690:76"/>
                     <hi>Atabalipa</hi> Priſoner, and that being frightned with the King her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's being condemned to death, ſhe had put her ſelf into a Canoo, with two Women to wait upon her, and that ſhe had landed upon the ſame Iſland, where I found this young Woman; that ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in this Cave, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by a Lyon which had there his Den; and that the two Women which had followed her, returned back in their Boat, without daring to take the Child whereof ſhe was delivered, and came back into the Province of <hi>Cuſco,</hi> where they related to <hi>Pizarro,</hi> the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate end of this Princeſs; at which he ſeemed to be ſenſibly afflicted. Theſe Circumſtances, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance that was between this Girl, and the Wife of <hi>Rominagui,</hi> made me eaſily comprehend, that this was the Child whereof the Queen of <hi>Peru</hi> was delivered and that ſhe might have a Name ſuitable to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59690:77"/>her Birth, I called her <hi>Zulemaide,</hi> which ſignifies, in the Language of the Countrey, full of Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>I would not take her with me to <hi>Diu,</hi> nor leave her in the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucca</hi> Iſlands, for fear ſome acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ſhould happen to her in my abſence, or that ſhe might ſuffer ſome inconveniency, by being in a beſieged Town. I therefore choſe rather to ſend her to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where I hoped to be my ſelf, in a ſhort time; I found near an Iſland where I touched for water, ſix <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſels, who were there for the ſame purpoſe; they were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by an Engliſh Captain called <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> and were returning for <hi>Europe.</hi> I would not ſlip ſo fair an opportunity, to ſend <hi>Zulemaide</hi> thither, it being the more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, becauſe two Veſſels of this Fleet were commanded by <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> Captains, the Name of the one was <hi>Vela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>quez,</hi> and the other <hi>Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez.</hi> I put her into the hands of a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59690:77"/>Souldier who ſerved long under me, and whoſe fidelity was well known to me, his name was <hi>John Becaio;</hi> our parting was very paſſionate, altho' I did not think I ſhould have loſt her, as I have done, without ever having been able to learn any news of her.</p>
                  <p>After the Siege of <hi>Diu</hi> was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>I</hi> went to the <hi>Molucca</hi>'s, where <hi>I</hi> made ſome ſtay, and from thence took paſſage to <hi>Portugal,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> could not hear any news, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Zulemaide,</hi> or of <hi>John Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caio. I</hi> ſearched for her in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and not having been able to diſcover any thing, which could quiet my mind; <hi>I</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> heard the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was ſending a Fleet to the <hi>Molucca's,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a Ship. <hi>I</hi> had, during this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, a quarrel with the Admiral of this Fleet, and ſeparated my ſelf from him in the Night, with a deſign to return for <hi>Lisbon.</hi> My
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59690:78"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:59690:78"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:59690:79"/>Lieutenant, to whom <hi>I</hi> had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated my deſign, oppoſed me, when he ſaw me change my Courſe. Upon this Conteſt we fell to words, and drew our Swords upon the Deck, our Souldiers took parties, each following his own inclination, and the fight was ſo bloody, that of above 500 which we were at firſt, there remained alive but 50, and thoſe almoſt all wounded; and for a full Complement of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, we were driven by ſo cruel a ſtorm, that we thought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very moment our Ship was going to ſink, we were driven near an Iſland, and altho' we knew it was not inhabited, yet we put out our Long-Boat to land there, fearing our Veſſel ſhould run a ground, coming too near the Land. It was almoſt night when we landed, and we paſſed the Night in great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, under ſome Banian Trees, the great Leaves of which defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us from the injuries of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59690:79"/>when it was day, we travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led further into the Iſland to get ſome freſh water, but we were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much amazed, to meet there that Lady, <hi>ſaid</hi> Mendez, <hi>(ſhewing the unknown Lady)</hi> vvith a Man in a Spaniſh habit, vvhich we afterwards found to be <hi>Don John de Serano,</hi> vvho vvent out vvith <hi>Magellan,</hi> to diſcover the <hi>Straights,</hi> to vvhich he gave his Name, they told us by vvhat accident they came into this Iſland, vve offered them to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them vvhither they pleaſed, and the Lady, in return offered us, to procure an employment for us, of the King of <hi>Borneo,</hi> her Father, if vve vvould conduct her into that Iſland. We uſed ſo much diligence in repairing the dammages vvhich the Tempeſt had done to our Ship, that in a fevv days, vve vvere in a condition to ſet ſail again. We vvent on Board with this Lady, and <hi>Don John de Serano,</hi> and, the Wind being favourable, vve arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59690:80"/>in a ſhort time at one of the Ports of this Iſland. When we had landed, we mounted upon Beaſts little differing from our European Stags, of which the great ones are made uſe of here, inſtead of Horſes, and they being very nimble, we came in a ſhort time to the King of <hi>Borneo</hi>'s Court, who gave us a favourable reception, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account, and for the ſake of his Daughter.</p>
                  <p>This Prince having ſent an Army under the Conduct of <hi>Don John de Serano</hi> againſt <hi>Mucitapan,</hi> King of the Iſland of <hi>Cuba.</hi> I had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſerve him in this War with my Ship, we overcome <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citapan,</hi> and after his death, this Lady was married to <hi>Don John,</hi> who was crowned King of <hi>Cuba.</hi> My Lady was baptized by one of the Prieſts, aboard my Veſſel, and was named <hi>Iſabella,</hi> all the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our Court followed our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and in a ſhort time, the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:59690:80"/>of the Chriſtian Religion, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etled in this Iſland, with as much freedom as in <hi>Spain.</hi> I remained ſtill at the Court of the new King, who had always a great value for me, looking upon me as a Man to whom he owed his life. Sometime afterwards the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, ſent <hi>Don Garcia</hi> to <hi>Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ala,</hi> where <hi>Don John</hi> kept his Courſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; but this Embaſſadour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of acquitting himſelf of the Commiſſion the Emperor had given him, minded nothing but his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt; and ſtole away the Princeſs <hi>Conſtantia.</hi> Daughter to King <hi>John.</hi> This Prince went after him with the lighteſt of his Ships, and I remained with the Queen, to take care of the Government of the Iſland in his abſence. Some days after the Kings departure, the Queen had notice that <hi>Conſtantia</hi> was carried away with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Don John;</hi> that he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to purſue <hi>Don Garcia,</hi> only
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59690:81"/>to take that opportunity, to go to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth's Court, who promiſed to marry one of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Daughters to him, provided he would quit to him the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the Iſland of <hi>Cuba.</hi> The Queen deſired me to conduct her to the Imperial Court, to demand juſtice of the Emperor, againſt <hi>Don John</hi> for his Treachery. I would not undertake this Voyage, until I had conſulted, how I was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my ſelf, with <hi>Don Lorenzo,</hi> who knew better than I, the humour of the Miniſters whereof the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror made uſe. We went to <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi> to ſeek for him, but we heard at our arrival, that he was gone from thence ſome days before, to find out <hi>Rominagui;</hi> and they tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us at the ſame time, that <hi>Don Eſtevan</hi> was his Father, and that he had retired himſelf into this <hi>Grotto,</hi> we ſent to deſire him to come to the Queen to <hi>Penco;</hi> in the mean while, I was very
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:59690:81"/>much amazed, that the Land-Lord of the Houſe where we lodged, was the ſame <hi>John Becaio,</hi> whom I had intruſted with the Princeſs <hi>Zulemaide.</hi> I asked him what he knew concerning her, one day when I was alone in my Chamber, and he thus related to me, what had hapned to him ſince our ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:59690:82"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Hiſtory of</hi> John Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caio.</head>
                  <p>YOU know, <hi>Seigneur,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> went on board <hi>Wincheſter</hi>'s Ship, with the Princeſs <hi>Zulemaide,</hi> of whom you gave me charge. <hi>I</hi> obſerved that this Privateer lookt upon her, with great earneſtneſs; but I never ſtirred far from her, and he durſt ſcarce ſpeak to her. This conſtraint being uneaſie to him, he endeavoured to find out ſome way to be rid of me, without uſing any violence; he ſtayed till we were in the narrow Seas, and putting upon the Coaſt of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> he ſent me on Shore in the Long-Boat, under pretence to buy him ſome Proviſions, which we wanted; it was above half a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59690:82"/>League from the place where <hi>I</hi> went on ſhore to St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> and it was already almoſt Night. <hi>I</hi> made all the haſte <hi>I</hi> could, that <hi>I</hi> might come to the Town before the Gates were ſhut. But <hi>I</hi> found in my way ſome Recruits, which were new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſed, who ſtripped me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaving me ſo much as my Shirt. <hi>I</hi> continued my Journey to St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> and thought my ſell very happy, that <hi>I</hi> got into the Town; <hi>I</hi> came under a Shop, where <hi>I</hi> would have ſheltered my ſelf, and have ſlept all Night. But <hi>I</hi> had not been there above half an hour, before <hi>I</hi> had been ſprinkled with ſome water, which was not very clean, this made me cry out aloud, which made the Miſtreſs of the Houſe put her head out at the Window, ſhe asked me what had befallen me; and after <hi>I</hi> had related to her my misfortunes, ſhe gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>I</hi> ſhould come up; paſſing by the Kitchin door, <hi>I</hi> ſaw prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59690:83"/>making for a great Supper, which gave me great Comfort; hoping <hi>I</hi> ſhould have my ſhare. However <hi>I</hi> ſeemed not to take any notice of it, but followed my Conductor to the firſt appartment, where I found a Woman which was pretty handſome, and about thirty years of age; ſhe made ſigns to me to come nearer to her, and having asked me, how <hi>I</hi> came to be reduced to ſo ſad a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I</hi> related to her in a few words, the adventures of my Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age She ſeemed to be much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at my misfortunes, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having given me a Cloak to cover me, ſhe told me, ſhe expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſupper one of her Friends, and that as ſoon as he was come, the meat ſhould be ſet upon the Table, and <hi>I</hi> ſhould eat with her. Whilſt we were thus in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there came a young Man of a pretty good Meen, <hi>I</hi> know not whether it was her Husband, or
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59690:83"/>her Gallant, but he looked upon me with a bended Brow; and after having asked this Woman who I was, and what I did there; he bid me get out of the Houſe, if I had not a mind to be ſoundly beaten, he took from me at the ſame time, the Cloak which had been given me, and having conducted me to the door of the Street, he ſhut it upon me. I walked ſome time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Town, not knowing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I went; and paſſing through a Church-Yard, I ſate down, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtay there the reſt of the Night. I had but juſt ſate down when I perceived a Lanthorn come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards me, if this ſight fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me, he who carried the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn, and his Companions, were not leſs afraid, for they took me for Spirit, and were juſt going to turn back, but they being ſix, came-to me with their Piſtols cock't, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, who was there? When they had heard my misfortune related,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59690:84"/>they thought I was proper to ſerve them in a deſign which they had, they made me go with them into the Church by a little door, of which they had the Key, they then took up a great ſtone, which cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the mouth of a Vault, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving let me down into it, they ſtuck the Candle which was in the Lanthorn againſt the Wall, and ſhewed me a Knight, which was in a Coffin of Lead, with all his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits and a great many Jewels, which they ordered me to take from him. I firſt took a Knights Croſs, ſet with Diamonds which I gave them, but having taken from him ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rings of value, which were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his fingers, I kept one for my ſelf, to make uſe of in caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. At the ſame time the Candle fell down, and went out, and the ſix Robbers went up immediately into the Church, and ſhut the Vault with the ſtone they had firſt raiſed. When I found my ſelf alone in a
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59690:84"/>place ſo full of horror, <hi>I</hi> took ſuch a fright, that <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> ſhould have died upon the place, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a ſhort time after, heard ſinging in the Church, <hi>I</hi> came to my ſelf again, and groped up the Stairs, when <hi>I</hi> was at the top, <hi>I</hi> cried out ſo loud, that the <hi>Canons,</hi> who were come to ſay Matins, took up the Stone to ſee what it was. So ſoon as <hi>I</hi> had a free paſſage, <hi>I</hi> ran away ſo ſwiftly, that they knew not what became of me. <hi>I</hi> went out by the little Door, which the Thieves had left open, but did not care to ſtay any longer in a Town, where <hi>I</hi> had been ſo ill u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; ſo <hi>I</hi> went round the Walls, and having found a breach, <hi>I</hi> went down through it into a Ditch, and from thence into the Fields. <hi>I</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a far off a Dung-Hill, which <hi>I</hi> went towards, and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by its heat, to recover my ſelf from the cold which I had endured. So ſoon as it was day. I went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59690:85"/>the Sea, and meeting a Coach with ſix Horſes, attended by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Horſemen, he, who was in it, ſeeing me in ſo bad an Equipage, commanded me to come to the Coach ſide. It was a reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who enquired of me all the particulars of my misfortune, with a great deal of Compaſſion. After I had told him all, he ordered one of his Servants to give me a Cloak, and ordered his Coachman, that I ſhould ride behind him, I accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied him as far as <hi>Vannes,</hi> where I deſired he would be pleaſed to buy my Ring, which was the only thing I had left; after having ſhewed it to a Jeweller, he kept it, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me a hundred Crowns, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of half went to cloath me, and the other half I ſubſiſted upon, till I went in to my own Country.</p>
                  <p>I endeavoured to find out a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience to go thither, and went to <hi>Dover,</hi> where I asked for <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> I heard there, that he had
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59690:85"/>paſſed the <hi>Straights,</hi> and that he was gone into the Mediterranean to cruiſe there; that which made me go into <hi>Portugal,</hi> was, to endeavour to get ſome money, before I went after the <hi>Privateer,</hi> I came to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where I drained the purſes of all my Friends, to put me into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to go the Voyage of <hi>Italy.</hi> I had the opportunity of a Ship, in which I went to <hi>Naples,</hi> and from thence by Land to <hi>Rome,</hi> but the Stock which I had carried, not being very great, it was ſoon ſpent, and I was forced to beg. My good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune brought me acquainted with another Begger, whoſe name was <hi>Bernardin,</hi> who conducted me to the Hoſpital to lodge, where I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came known to the Directors of it. I behaved my ſelf with ſo much cunning, that I was employed to beg for all the Hoſpital, in which employment, I found my account many ways, I made an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with ſome of the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableſt
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59690:86"/>Women in the whole Town, who made me from time to time ſmall preſents; of the mony which was given me, I carried but two thirds to the Hoſpital, and I divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that which I kept for my ſelf, into three parts, one part was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted for play, and my other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, the ſecond to buy me Cloaths and Linnen, and the third I kept in bank, to make uſe of when I wanted an employment. I had been but too happy, if this life had laſted always, but by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, <hi>Velaſquez</hi> found me one day in a Church, and having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me his Alms, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, he went from me two or three ſteps, but came back again to me, and asked me how much he had given me? Sir, ſaid I, it is two pence I have from your Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Give it me back again,</hi> replied Velaſquez, <hi>and I will give thee a Piſtole.</hi> I thought he had known me, ſince he gave me ſuch great Alms.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:59690:86"/>But however, I thought it beſt to let him explain himſelf before I did, I only gave him the two pence, and took the Piſtole he gave me, and ſeeing he went away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſaying any thing more, I kept the ſame ſilence. Four days after this, meeting him in the ſtreet, he accoſted me, and deſired me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver from him a Note to a young ſtrange Lady, which was lately arrived in <hi>Rome,</hi> and who lived in great retirement. I repreſented to him what a hazard I ſhould run, in venturing to do ſuch a thing to a Woman of ſo great Vertue as ſhe was, and that <hi>I</hi> could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a charge ſo oppoſite to the profeſſion <hi>I</hi> followed. But he made me ſo many promiſes, and ſpake ſo many civil words to me, ſwearing ſo often he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake me; that <hi>I</hi> could not refuſe doing him this Service. The next day <hi>I</hi> found the Lady at <hi>Maſs,</hi> and being accuſtomed to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59690:87"/>give her often little Images or Prayers to invite her to liberality. She took the Note without open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, thinking it was ſomething of the ſame nature, with what I uſed to preſent every day. The next day I came to her, to ſee how ſhe had taken the thing, and asked her Charity as I uſed to do, but ſhe called me by ſeveral op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Names, and proteſted ſhe would have me puniſhed, if I ever appeared again in her ſight. And I aſſure you that altho' I have without fear gone through the greateſt Dangers, yet this young Beauty made me tremble, and took from me the Confidence to give her any anſwer. This ſtory came to the Ears of the Director of the Hoſpital, who after having rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me ſeverely for it, would have had me whipped, and ſent to Priſon, but I choſe rathcr to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and quit the profits which I made of the employment he had
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59690:87"/>given me. I went to give a viſit to <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> and after having made my ſelf known to him, I asked him for news of <hi>Zulemaid.</hi> He told me <hi>Wincheſter</hi> was fallen in love with her, that he had ſent me to buy Victuals only to rid himſelf of me, and that he had paſſed into the Mediterranean, to avoid meeting with you, and not to be forced to reſtore her. I deſired him to tell me if ſhe were yet in the hands of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> And he told me, that he having been forced to land on the Coaſt of <hi>Africa,</hi> his Ship had been attacqued by four <hi>Gallies,</hi> which came from <hi>Algiers,</hi> and that they had made the Princeſs a ſlave. I reſolved to live with <hi>Valaſquez,</hi> that I might the eaſier find a way to hear of <hi>Zulemaide,</hi> and he, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I vvas reſolute, vvas glad to make uſe of me. I accompanied him alvvays by night, vvhen he vvent upon any night Intreague; and to bring my ſelf into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:59690:88"/>Reputation vvith him, I made uſe of this pleaſant Artifice, <hi>I</hi> poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed four <hi>Bravos</hi> of my acquaintance, who came to aſſault us; <hi>I</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately drew my Sword, and vvent tovvards them vvith great reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. After having fenced vvith them ſome time, they turned their backs, and fled, as vve had agreed they ſhould; this made <hi>Velaſquez</hi> have a great opinion of my cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and made me paſs vvith him for an undaunted Souldier. The next morning being at his riſing, he gave me one of his ſuits of Cloaths, vvhich vvas vvorth above an hundred Ducates, to ſhevv me his gratefulneſs, and <hi>I</hi> vvent imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the Tavern vvith my four Friends, and treated them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry highly. <hi>Velaſquez</hi> blazed abroad this Action every vvhere, and ſpoke of me vvith ſuch great Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, that the greateſt Men of the City vvere glad to have my Friendſhip. <hi>I</hi> vvent every morning
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:59690:88"/>to the Tennis Court, vvhere <hi>I</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and every one acquieſced in my judgment, for fear of diſpleaſing me. <hi>I</hi> vvas put upon all dangerous adventures, and <hi>I</hi> vvas often forced to venture my Life, to keep up the reputation vvhich <hi>I</hi> had acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But going often to dine at the Tables of the great Lords, <hi>I</hi> met at the Table vvith a <hi>Buffoon,</hi> who had been vvell received every vvhere, he ſometimes ſpeaking things vvhich vvere diverting. <hi>I</hi> never loved that ſort of People, and having one day met him abroad, I laughed at him, and called him fool. He anſvvered me inſolently, and I gave him a box on the Ear, vvhich <hi>I</hi> thought vvould have throvvn him upon the ground. A <hi>Bravo</hi> vvho vvas there, took his part vvith ſo much Warmth, that <hi>I</hi> vvas forced to come to blovvs vvith him; vve vvent to fight in the great Place before St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, and vve were both vvoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:59690:89"/>in the firſt attack, but vvith great difference, for he geve me only a Cut upon my Head vvhich ſtunned me, and at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, I ran him thorovv the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vvith my Svvord, and made him fall at my feet wallowing in his own blood. There came by at the ſame time, a Company of <hi>Catch-poles,</hi> vvho came upon me, and forced me avvay to Priſon. All the other Adventures vvhich had happened to me at <hi>Rome,</hi> vvere added to this, to blacken me; and I vvas accuſed for corrupting the Youth of <hi>Rome.</hi> But my Enemy recovering of his Wound, they vvere contented vvith only baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me from the City for ſome years When I vvas come out of Priſon, I vvent to <hi>Velaſquez,</hi> vvho vvas juſt upon his departure from <hi>Rome;</hi> I took this opportunity, and vvent vvith him to <hi>Venice.</hi> I could not hear there any nevvs of <hi>Zulemaid,</hi> vvhich made me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59690:89"/>to return to the <hi>Indies,</hi> that I might relate to you vvhat had been the Deſtiny of that Princeſs. I vvent to <hi>Naples,</hi> vvhere I found a paſſage for <hi>Sevil.</hi> I vvaited there, for the going off of the <hi>Gallions,</hi> upon which I embarqued. They came to an Anchor before <hi>Penco,</hi> where <hi>Valdivia</hi> then was, I could not hear of you there, which made me reſolve to ſtay there until I could. I have married there a Wife, whoſe firſt Husband kept an Inn, which made me have a mind to take up the ſame trade. I find ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvell my account by it, by the tricks my Wife has taught me to uſe in it. When there comes any Paſſengers, ſo ſoon as their Horſes have any Oats given to them, I ſend my Hens to the Stable, who eat with them without being invited. I kill every year five or ſix Hogs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I make a ſpiced ſort of Pudding, which laſts all the Winter: The Shepherds round about us furnish
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:59690:90"/>me with meat, at a very eaſie rate; for when they have any Sheep or Goats ſick, or ready to die with Age, they immediately bring them to me. Thoſe who eat of this meat, find it often hard and tough, but when a Man is hungry, he eats any thing We have an hundred Hens, whoſe ſtale Eggs we ſell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer than they do freſh Eggs at <hi>Lis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon.</hi> We keep Pigeons, Capons, and Pheaſants, but theſe are only for the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> or for the Principal Officers of his Army. This is the life I lead. I wiſh I could tell you better news of the Princeſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you intruſted me, but you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be very well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that it was not in my power to hinder her from falling into the misfortune ſhe has done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus</hi> John Becaio <hi>finiſhed his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> added Mendez, <hi>and I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to go to</hi> Conſtantinople. <hi>For altho' it looks as if it were impoſſible to get her out of the</hi> Seraglio, <hi>I will
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:59690:90"/>do it, or I will periſh in the attempt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When <hi>Mendez</hi> had made an end of ſpeaking, thoſe who had been liſtning to him, would have retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the <hi>Grotto,</hi> but a great noiſe which they heard towards the Sea, made them ſearch into the Cauſe. They went to the bottom of the Hill, and when they were upon the ſhore, they ſaw nothing which gave them any Light. After having liſtned ſome time, they obſerved this noiſe came from ſome place under ground, and was formed of confuſed Voices, but they ſearched no further into it, they knowing the entry of that Cave was on the other ſide of the Rock, and it was impoſſible for them to go thither, the feigned <hi>Don Garcia</hi> having taken away <hi>Don Eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans</hi> Boat, ſo they were forced to go back to their <hi>Grotto,</hi> to take a ſlender Meal which was provided for them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:59690:91"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome <hi>Novels</hi> and <hi>Plays</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>NOVELS.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>ZElinda</hi> a fam'd <hi>Romance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Happy Slave,</hi> in three Parts.</item>
               <item>3 Count <hi>Brion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 Count <hi>Gabales.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Hatige,</hi> or, the Amours of the King of <hi>Tamaran</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 Madam <hi>Lavalier</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 Madam and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 Mad. <hi>Colonna</hi>'s Memoirs.</item>
               <item>9 Queen of <hi>Majorca,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
               <item>10 Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11 Heroine Muſquitier.</item>
               <item>12 Princeſs of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:59690:91"/>
               <item>13 Obliging Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>14 Fatal Prudence.</item>
               <item>15 Princeſs of <hi>Fez.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. Diſorders of Love.</item>
               <item>17 Triumph of Love.</item>
               <item>18 Victorious Lovers.</item>
               <item>19 <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Almanzaida.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20 Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21 <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> or, the Defender of his Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>22 <hi>Nicoſtratis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23 Amorous Abbeſs.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>Homais</hi> Queen of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>25 Pilgrim, in two Parts.</item>
               <item>26 <hi>Meroveus,</hi> Prince of the Blood-Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>27 Life of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>28 Extravagant Poet.</item>
               <item>29 <hi>Memoires Gallant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>30 Inſtruction for a young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</item>
               <item>31 Love Letters from the <hi>Cavalier</hi> to the <hi>Nun.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>32 Gallant Ladies; or, the Mutual Conference: In two Parts.</item>
               <item>33 St. <hi>Lewis;</hi> or, the Politick
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:59690:92"/>Conduct of Queen <hi>Blanch.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Tartuff,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Puritan.</item>
               <item>2 Forc'd Marriage, or the Jealous Bridegroom.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Engliſh Monſieur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 All miſtaken or the Mad Couple.</item>
               <item>5 Generous Enemies, or the Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Lovers.</item>
               <item>6 The Plain-Dealer.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Sertorius,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Nero,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>9 <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hanibal</hi>'s Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Gloriana</hi> or the Court of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11 <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</item>
               <item>12 <hi>Mythridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 <hi>Oedipus</hi> King of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14 <hi>Caeſar Borgia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15 <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or the Force of Love.</item>
               <item>16 Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> or the Witty Falſe One.</item>
               <item>17. The Fond Husband, or the Plotting Siſters.</item>
               <item>18 Eſquire <hi>Old-Sap,</hi> or, the Night-Adventures.</item>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:59690:92"/>
               <item>19 Fool turn'd Critick.</item>
               <item>20 Virtuous Wife, or Good Luck at Laſt.</item>
               <item>21 The Fatal Wager.</item>
               <item>22 <hi>Andromache.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23 Country Wit.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>Caliſto,</hi> or, the Chaſte Nymph.</item>
               <item>25 Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
               <item>26 Ambitious Stateſman; or, the Loyal Favourite.</item>
               <item>27 Miſery of Civil War.</item>
               <item>28 The Murder of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>29 <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>30 <hi>Hamlet</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>31 The Orphan, or the Unhappy Marriage.</item>
               <item>32 The Soldiers Fortune.</item>
               <item>33 <hi>Tamerlain</hi> the Great.</item>
               <item>34 Mr. <hi>Limberham,</hi> or, the Kind Keeper.</item>
               <item>35 Miſtaken Husband.</item>
               <item>36 Notes of <hi>Morocco,</hi> by the Wits.</item>
               <item>37 <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Favourite.</item>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:59690:93"/>
               <item>38 Virtue Betray'd, or, <hi>Anna Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>39 King <hi>Leare.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>40 <hi>Abdellazor,</hi> or the <hi>Moor</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</item>
               <item>41 Town Fop, or Sir <hi>Tim. Tawdery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>42 <hi>Rare en tout,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Comedy.</item>
               <item>43 <hi>Moor</hi> of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>44 Countrey Wife.</item>
               <item>45 City Politicks.</item>
               <item>46 Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>47 Rehearſal.</item>
               <item>48 King, and no King.</item>
               <item>49 <hi>Philaſter,</hi> or Love lies a Bleeding.</item>
               <item>50 Maids Tragedy,</item>
               <item>51 Grateful Servant.</item>
               <item>52 Strange Diſcovery.</item>
               <item>53 Atheiſt, or, the ſecond Part of the Soldiers Fortune.</item>
               <item>54 Wit without Money.</item>
               <item>55 Little Thief.</item>
               <item>56 Valliant <hi>Scot,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>57 <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>58 <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>59 Amorous Prince.</item>
               <item>60 <hi>Dutch</hi> Lovers.</item>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:59690:93"/>
               <item>61 Woman Bully.</item>
               <item>62 Reformation.</item>
               <item>63 <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>64 Love Tricks.</item>
               <item>65 <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>66 Fatal Jealouſie.</item>
               <item>67 Monſieur <hi>Ragou.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>68 Iſland Queen, or, <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>69 Empreſs of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>70 Common-Wealth of Women.</item>
               <item>71 The Noble Stranger.</item>
               <item>72 Duke of <hi>Millan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>73 The Knave in Grain.</item>
               <item>74 Amends for Ladies.</item>
               <item>75 <hi>Manamochy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>76 The Emperor of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>77 The Wedding.</item>
               <item>78 St. <hi>Patrick</hi> for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>79 <hi>Albumazor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>80 The Tragedy of <hi>Albertus.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:59690:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:59690:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
